<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-12T10:16:08+02:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Matej Latin</title><subtitle>Matej Latin is a Senior Product designer at GitLab and is based in Ljubljana, Slovenia. He writes about design, minimalism and typography.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My favourite books of 2020</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2021/04/08/my-favourite-books-of-2020/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My favourite books of 2020" /><published>2021-04-08T21:56:54+02:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T21:56:54+02:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2021/04/08/my-favourite-books-of-2020</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2021/04/08/my-favourite-books-of-2020/">&lt;figure class=&quot;full-bleed-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fav-books-2020.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my latest personal project launched, I finally have some time to reflect on the books I read in 2020. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/user/year_in_books/2020/11006629&quot;&gt;I only managed to read 19 books&lt;/a&gt; in the past year. I say “only” because my goals is to read 25 per year. This is a list of books that I &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; in 2020, they weren’t necessarily published in 2020. They’re not sorted in any order, I just really liked these four books. This is the fourth year that I’m writing such post. You can see my favourite books from the past years here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017/&quot;&gt;My favourite books of 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018/&quot;&gt;My favourite books of 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2020/01/26/my-favourite-books-of-2019/&quot;&gt;My favourite books of 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lab-rats&quot;&gt;Lab Rats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1568031789l/52932046._SX318_SY475_.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lab Rats by Dan Lyons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Lab Rats by Dan Lyons &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became a fan of Dan Lyons after reading his book Disrupted which made it to the list of my favourite books of 2018. His writing and his voice really resonates with me. I love that he covers controversial topics and isn’t afraid to attack commonly accepted “norms.” This time, he looks at the Silicon Valley companies and how they’re destroying the workplace but selling it to us as “it’s the hip thing to do.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open-plan offices are so cool right? Everyone works with everyone else in the company and collaboration drastically improves because of that. It also promotes transparency because there are &lt;em&gt;literally&lt;/em&gt; no walls. Employees in such offices feel like they’re part of a cool company that “gets” what’s hip and cool. So they redesigned the offices into an open-plan layout to make the employees feel more engaged working for such a cool company. What a load of bullshit! &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west/&quot;&gt;Open-plan offices are the modern-day sweatshops&lt;/a&gt;. That’s it! They’re not designed to make the employees feel better or work better, they’re designed to fill in as many people as possible and thus reduce the cost per employee. This is just one of the things that Lyons attacks. The others are the greed, the new tech oligarchs, the dehumanisation of workers and many others. Highly recommended if you work for a tech company that tries to emulate the bullshit that the tech giants have been pushing down our throats for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t agree with everything that Lyons attacks in this book. For example, I believe that the Lean methodology does help reduce waste at tech companies. But his main point is that instead of our workplace improving through decades, it’s actually getting worse. We work more than the past generations but we get paid less. We can’t even dream about retiring and receiving a pension. All the progress in automation and robotics has had little impact on improving people’s work and lives. Something’s terribly wrong and we need to fix it. Thankfully, Lyons offers ideas and examples of how certain companies try to do the opposite and have a positive impact on the world, without exhausting their employees and without being driven by greed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/52932046-lab-rats&quot;&gt;Lab Rats on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outliers&quot;&gt;Outliers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1344266315l/3228917.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Outliers by Malcolm Gladwell&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Outliers by Malcolm Gladwell &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2020 was the year when I first read a book by Malcolm Gladwell. I heard many good things about him and his books but just never took the time to actually get and read one. This changed one day when I decided to go to a local bookshop and see if I can find an interesting book. It’s something I love to do as I then always remember the experience of finding and buying the book and all the excitement that comes with that. Interestingly, this wasn’t the first book of his that I read. The first one that truly caught my eye was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22433143-david-and-goliath&quot;&gt;David and Goliath&lt;/a&gt;. Although I thoroughly enjoyed it, Outliers stuck with me more. Both are excellent though, I just didn’t want to include two books of the same author on this list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-1&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gladwell seriously knows how to write. Holy shit! I don’t know what exactly it is about his writing but it’s so easy an enjoyable. Reading his books makes you want to keep going. Even when you read the chapter that you wanted to read in a day, you can’t wait to get to the next one. I always read his books so quickly just because of that. I generally tend to read for about 30 minutes each day. But when I was reading his books, I ended up reading for one hour, sometimes even longer. He does a masterful job of telling stories that don’t seem related at first. Then, in the end, his wraps it all together and hits you with a punch you didn’t expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-1&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I loved about this book the most is the message itself. He starts going through different stories about people and how they became really good at something. Stories of outliers. Something that seems to tie the stories together as you read, is how he always comes to the conclusion that outliers become outliers because of many different factors. Some are internal (people’s motivations), others external (opportunities). In the end, he concludes the book with his story and wraps it all together in an emotional way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outliers aren’t outliers because of one singular reason. They’re outliers because of their past, their family’s past, the people that surround them and the opportunities that they had. In a way, they’re not outliers at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/3228917-outliers&quot;&gt;Outliers on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-conquest-of-happiness&quot;&gt;The Conquest of Happiness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1495532262l/16234597.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Conquest of Happiness by Bertrand Russel&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Conquest of Happiness by Bertrand Russel &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had this book on my to-read list for a long time. It’s a highly rated book and the topic of happiness which has always attracted me. That’s because I’ve been witnessing people being miserable their whole lives and not doing anything about that. I always thought &lt;em&gt;that’s so strange, why don’t they try to solve the problems that seem to be making their lives a misery?&lt;/em&gt; I guess that’s a bit naive now when I look back. Especially because not every problem can be solved, or maybe it can’t be solved easily. So yes, people turn to easy solutions like ignoring their problems, drinking and generally destructive behaviour. First published in 1930, this book talks about all that. Russell is actually most well-known for being a genius mathematician, but he was also a historian, a philosopher and a rationalist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-2&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russell starts out with listing things that make people unhappy including &lt;em&gt;competition&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;boredom and excitement&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;fatigue&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;envy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;the sense of sin&lt;/em&gt; and others. It was interesting to read his thoughts about these things and recognise how they make me or other people unhappy. The topic about competition stuck with me the most. Why are people so competitive? Why does everyone want more money? Why does everything need to be bigger and stronger than everyone else’s? Why do we sacrifice so much to become “successful?” Here’s a line that I underlined and want to keep in my mind at all times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Success can only be one ingredient in happiness, and is too dearly purchased if all the other ingredients have been sacrificed to obtain it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He then explores things that make people happy and lists &lt;em&gt;zest&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;affection&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;family&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;work&lt;/em&gt; as the main things. Interestingly, success, money and the things that people usually chase aren’t on this list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-2&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stop competing with everyone else, find a good balance between boredom and excitement, don’t work too much, don’t be envious, get rid of the sense of sin, stop caring about what others think. Approach life with zest, dedicate your time to your work, your family and your interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/51783.The_Conquest_of_Happiness&quot;&gt;The Conquest of Happiness on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-man-called-ove&quot;&gt;A Man Called Ove&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1496137759l/25555839.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A Man Called Ove by Fredrik Backman&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A Man Called Ove by Fredrik Backman &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally don’t read fiction books. In a way, I always felt like “I don’t have time for such books”, meaning that there’s little to be learned from them. Well, my wife recommended this one and I realised how wrong I was. How silly of me to assume that there’s nothing to be learned from stories, even if they’re made up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-3&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backman is a Swedish writer and this is a story about a grumpy old man. I don’t want to share too much about the story because I could easily spoil it for you. The coolest thing about it is that it drops you into the life of Ove at a certain point and it unravels what’s going on piece by piece. Sometimes it switched into what happened in the past when Ove was a child or a young man to give more background on why he is the way he is. He might seem like a typical annoying old man at first, but your heart warms up towards him as you read the story. Daily Mail described it as “Warm, funny, and unbearably moving”, and I think they nailed it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-3&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thing that stuck with me the most from this book is: every person needs to have principles to navigate through life. But times changes and our principles need to be flexible. We may need to update, or even abandon some of them as we progress through our lives. I read this book in a hard period of my life and it really touched me. It got me back into reading fiction, mostly because it’s a story that a man can relate to. Sadly, there are too few stories like these out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25555839-a-man-called-ove&quot;&gt;A Man Called Ove on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So not everything in 2020 was shit. I read more than enough good books to consider for this list. Out of 19 I read in total, I narrowed them down to seven and then further to four. They’re just four, but they’re really good. I hope this gives you a couple of ideas on what to read next and that you’ll enjoy whatever you pick.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Books" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I decided to sell my book on Lulu.com</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/12/01/why-i-decided-to-sell-my-book-on-lulu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I decided to sell my book on Lulu.com" /><published>2020-12-01T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/12/01/why-i-decided-to-sell-my-book-on-lulu</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/12/01/why-i-decided-to-sell-my-book-on-lulu/">&lt;p&gt;Going to a bookshop is a magical experience. Book prices are even higher there, I know, but there’s a magical feeling when you walk out with a new book in your hands. I can recollect most of such moments from the past, the one when I bought Digital Minimalism by Cal Newport in Edinburgh is the most memorable. It turned out to be the last book that I bought there before moving back to Slovenia so it’s a bittersweet memory. That’s what makes it even more special. Unlike an eBook, a physical book is an object that can be admired. It’s tangible, you open it up and it has a gentle smell no matter if it’s new or old. The smell changes as the book ages, but it’s always a lovely smell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/digital-minimalism.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cal Newport’s Digital Minimalism turned out to be the last book I bought in my favourite bookshop in Edinburgh.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Cal Newport’s Digital Minimalism turned out to be the last book I bought in my favourite bookshop in Edinburgh. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an author’s perspective, a book feels more real when you hold it in your hand and think “I made this.” That and my love for printed books is why I always wanted to create a printed version of my book about web typography. It’s so much harder than creating an eBook where you focus on the content. For a printed book to look good you need to pick the right material and the right finish for the cover and the pages. You need to think about page numbering, and footers, and headers, how to fit illustrations on a limited size of a page and how to optimise the number of pages. My book originally had more than 250 pages and I gradually reduced it to 232. Not by taking the content away but with better illustration placement and optimising margins and font sizes. You don’t need to do any of these things for the eBook!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-quality-of-the-materials-reflects-the-quality-of-the-book&quot;&gt;The quality of the materials reflects the quality of the book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent two whole months working on the second edition of my book at the beginning of 2018. Most of those two months went into improving the printed book. After that, I had to decide who my printer would be. I had experimented with Amazon’s print on demand, as well as Blurb’s. Both kinda sucked. Amazon’s print quality was poor. The cover looked cheap and so did the paper used for the interior pages. After investing so much time in making the book, I didn’t want it to look and feel cheap. I wanted the quality of the print to reflect the effort I put in making the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blurb was a bit better, so the very first printed books that I sold were printed in batches through Blurb and distributed manually. By that, I mean that I was carrying a huge box of around 50 books to the post office every week. When I lived in Camden, this meant a 30-minute walk with a box that weighed around 25 kg! I couldn’t keep up with it, I needed a better solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bwt-books-stack.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The second and improved quality edition of my web typography book printed by Lulu.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The second and improved quality edition of my web typography book printed by Lulu. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I did more research, I discovered Lulu. There, I was able to choose between a glossy and matte finish for the book cover. I chose matte. I could also choose the finish for the interior pages and I chose the coated one. I ordered a couple of test copies and was pleasantly surprised when they arrived. The matte cover finish had a velvety feel to it. It looked and felt sophisticated. The pages were slightly glossy because of the coating and it made the colours stand out. I loved it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;full-bleed-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/bwt-book-details.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The detail shots of my web typography book’s interior pages.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The detail shots of my web typography book’s interior pages. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-distribution&quot;&gt;The distribution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manual distribution turned out to be a huge endeavour. I had no idea that so many people wanted to buy the printed version of my book. Even the customers who already bought the eBook were ordering the printed version. There was a huge demand for it and I couldn’t keep up. A book would sometimes get lost during the delivery and I had to arrange a replacement. Two or three out of 100 books that I sent out would get lost. It’s not a lot, but it becomes significant when you’re running your business as a side gig. So when I reintroduced the printed version of the book this autumn, I decided to sell it directly through Lulu’s web platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;benefits-of-lulucom&quot;&gt;Benefits of Lulu.com&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lulu is print on demand which means that when a customer places an order, it will be directed to the print shop that is closest to that customer. They print the book and send it. The costs of shipping are lower and the delivery time shorter which results in more happy customers. If something goes wrong with the delivery the customer reaches out to Lulu and they take care of the problem. Their customer support is a bit slow but good. Now I have more time to focus on creating new things because Lulu takes care of the whole process. I can continue to offer the printed version of my book and I’m happy with the quality of the print and so were the customers that ordered the book so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you want to get the printed version of &lt;em&gt;Better Web Typography for a Better Web&lt;/em&gt; you can do so on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/matej-latin/better-web-typography-for-a-better-web-second-edition/paperback/product-y98kdp.html?page=1&amp;amp;pageSize=4&quot;&gt;Lulu.com&lt;/a&gt;. I hope you’ll enjoy it and appreciate the quality of the print as much as I do.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you prefer eBooks, you can get it on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com/web-typography-book/&quot;&gt;official Better Web Type website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Business" /><category term="Better-Web-Type" /><summary type="html">Going to a bookshop is a magical experience. Book prices are even higher there, I know, but there’s a magical feeling when you walk out with a new book in your hands. I can recollect most of such moments from the past, the one when I bought Digital Minimalism by Cal Newport in Edinburgh is the most memorable. It turned out to be the last book that I bought there before moving back to Slovenia so it’s a bittersweet memory. That’s what makes it even more special. Unlike an eBook, a physical book is an object that can be admired. It’s tangible, you open it up and it has a gentle smell no matter if it’s new or old. The smell changes as the book ages, but it’s always a lovely smell.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://matejlatin.co.uk/bwt-cover" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://matejlatin.co.uk/bwt-cover" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I don’t do Black Friday sales</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/11/28/why-i-dont-do-black-friday-sales/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I don’t do Black Friday sales" /><published>2020-11-28T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2020-11-28T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/11/28/why-i-dont-do-black-friday-sales</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/11/28/why-i-dont-do-black-friday-sales/">&lt;p&gt;Black Friday is often referred to as the “consumerism holiday” and I can’t help myself but this sounds so wrong to me. The level of consumerism that we got to in the world today is absurd. Maybe I think that because of my minimalist mentality and lifestyle. Minimalism is something that has attracted me for years now and it became a fundamental part of my life. This doesn’t mean that I never buy anything on Black Friday sales, I do. But it’s usually something that I have been thinking about buying for a while. When you adopt the minimalist mentality, a buying decision is never an impulsive one. I think 10 times whether I really need something before I buy it. This is the complete opposite of what the whole Black Friday thing promotes and what it means to most people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there’s a huge misalignment between what Black Friday represents and my lifestyle. I would like that people who buy my book make a rational decision when they do so. I don’t want it to be an impulsive purchase only because it costs $5 instead of $50. If you think you need to learn about web typography and my book looks like something that’ll help with that, go ahead and buy it. Don’t buy it because there’s a huge discount and you found it in a &lt;em&gt;Best Black Friday deals for designers&lt;/em&gt; blog post. And in the end, you never actually read it. Or worse, you never even &lt;em&gt;start&lt;/em&gt; reading it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/better-web-type-book-cover-paperback.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The second edition of my typography book called Better Web Typography for a Better Web.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The second edition of my typography book called Better Web Typography for a Better Web. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason why I don’t do Black Friday sales is that I discount the book every month when I send out my web typography newsletter. The discount is significant but not absurd. It’s usually around 30%. An absurd discount like 90% can also make people question the quality of the product. I don’t want that. I invested a lot of time into writing and illustrating it and I want my customers to recognise that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I can’t afford your book, &lt;br /&gt;can I get an extra discount?&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Someone&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I receive a different email. Someone will write to me asking for an extra discount because they live in a country where a price tag of $20 represents their weekly earnings. I don’t give them more discount. If the person writing to me is sincere, I send them the book for free. It happened many times in the past and I intend to continue doing this. I didn’t write my book with intentions that people generally have when they write books—fortune, fame and recognition. I wrote it so that other designers could learn about typography faster and better than I did. The fact that it brings me some extra cash is a bonus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you live in a country where $20 is a ton of money, let me know. We’ll see what we can do. But if you don’t, know that when you buy the book it helps support my work and one day I’ll be able to dedicate more time to it. This way I’ll be able to reach and help out even more designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can get the eBook version of my book on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com/web-typography-book/&quot;&gt;official Better Web Type website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;or you can get the printed version on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lulu.com/en/us/shop/matej-latin/better-web-typography-for-a-better-web-second-edition/paperback/product-y98kdp.html?page=1&amp;amp;pageSize=4&quot;&gt;Lulu.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Minimalism" /><category term="Business" /><category term="Better-Web-Type" /><summary type="html">Black Friday is often referred to as the “consumerism holiday” and I can’t help myself but this sounds so wrong to me. The level of consumerism that we got to in the world today is absurd. Maybe I think that because of my minimalist mentality and lifestyle. Minimalism is something that has attracted me for years now and it became a fundamental part of my life. This doesn’t mean that I never buy anything on Black Friday sales, I do. But it’s usually something that I have been thinking about buying for a while. When you adopt the minimalist mentality, a buying decision is never an impulsive one. I think 10 times whether I really need something before I buy it. This is the complete opposite of what the whole Black Friday thing promotes and what it means to most people.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://matejlatin.co.uk/bwt-cover" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://matejlatin.co.uk/bwt-cover" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My favourite books of 2019</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2019/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My favourite books of 2019" /><published>2020-01-18T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2020-01-18T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2020/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2019/">&lt;figure class=&quot;full-bleed-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/fav-books-2019.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to my Goodreads’ &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/user/year_in_books/2019&quot;&gt;My Year in Books 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; report, I read 24 books last year. That’s five more than the year before but still one short from reaching my goal of 25. I guess I’m slowly getting there. This is a list of my favourite books that I &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; in 2019, not of books that were published in 2019 (although some of them were). And they’re not sorted in any order at all, the same as my lists for &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017/&quot;&gt;my favourite books of 2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018/&quot;&gt;my favourite books of 2018&lt;/a&gt; weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;company-of-one&quot;&gt;Company of One&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1534280579l/41144788._SY475_.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Company of One by Paul Jarvis&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Company of One by Paul Jarvis &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the very first book that I read in 2019 as it was released in January and I preordered it. I’ve been following Paul Jarvis for a long time as he’s been an inspiration ever since I stumbled upon him. This is his first book ever but I always liked his writing style and honesty. I’ve also been exploring the entrepreneurship waters for the last few years so I wanted to see what Jarvis’ approach is. Maybe there’s something cool to learn from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, of course, there was. Jarvis challenges the whole ever-growing business that we, as a society, are fans of. You know, the stories about the Facebooks and similar companies. How one geek created an app and became an overnight success because of their genius idea. Jarvis takes the opposite approach. He “only” has his own small company where it’s just him. He does collaborate with a small number of other people that he trusts but he intentionally remained a company of one. He argues that a company should continually be made better instead of bigger and makes a compelling case where he prioritises &lt;em&gt;a rich life over the riches&lt;/em&gt;, as Cal Newport wrote in his review of the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first book that came to my mind when I was preparing this list and it’s for one sole reason. It fundamentally changed my view of entrepreneurship. Since I read this book, I started shaping my own business strategy that aligns with a lot of what Jarvis argues for. I realise that often, entrepreneurs feed their egos with their business “successes” which are often measured by the size of the company and its revenue. I want to take the opposite approach now. I want to have my own business to help me fulfil my purpose: support my family and live a modest but happy life with meaningful relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/41144788-company-of-one&quot;&gt;Company of One on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;digital-minimalism&quot;&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight img-border&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1578318088l/44160076._SX318_.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Digital Minimalism by Cal Newport&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Digital Minimalism by Cal Newport &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we mentioned Cal Newport and his opinion of Paul Jarvis’ book, let’s take a look at his &lt;em&gt;Digital Minimalism&lt;/em&gt; next. I’ve been a fan of Newport’s ideas ever since I read his book Deep Work (which made it to my list of favs in 2018). Digital Minimalism was his latest and brand new book when I bought it in the busiest bookshop in Edinburgh that I persistently visited almost every week. One of the coolest things about buying a physical book is the recollection of the shopping experience—in my case, it turned out to be the last book that I bought in my favourite bookshop before I left Edinburgh to move back to Slovenia. It’s a bittersweet memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-1&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual for Newport, he presents the problem he’s writing about in a clear way. In this case, it’s the society’s relationship with everything digital, but especially social media. It’s coming to the point where billions of people are building unhealthy habits that lead to lives cluttered with junk, instead of meaningful relationships. In the second part, he gives advice on how to move away from that and he doesn’t stray away from his usual actionable approach. That’s what I like about him the most—he presents practical things that one should do to solve their problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-1&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newport leans heavily on Henry David Thoreau’s ideas from Walden. I think that the following quote he included describes his book well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The cost of a thing is the amount of what I call life which is required to be exchanged for it, immediately or in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Henry David Thoreau&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put this in practice, I was never attracted by the idea of owning an Apple Watch because of exactly this way of thinking. It’s another item in my life that would constantly call for my attention, that I’d need to manage so it doesn’t overwhelm me and so on. So I would need to trade moments of my life to spend with yet another device. I didn’t want that. My iPhone alone is a distraction so tempting that it nearly turned me into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie/&quot;&gt;buzz junkie&lt;/a&gt;, so I need to manage it rigidly to prevent it from sucking my life away from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/44160076-digital-minimalism&quot;&gt;Digital Minimalism on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quiet&quot;&gt;Quiet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1547203165l/17204619._SY475_.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Quiet by Susan Cain&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Quiet by Susan Cain &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually a book that my wife bought but it was also on my “to-read” list. I know for a while now that I’m an introverted person so I wanted to learn more about this characteristic that is sometimes seen as a “disability” preventing some to act as “normal” people in social situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-2&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly to &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2016/07/07/a-tale-of-a-colour-blind-designer/&quot;&gt;my colour blindness&lt;/a&gt;, being an introvert can be used as a superpower. But I didn’t realise this until I read this book. Susan Cain challenges the ever-likeable extroverted fella as being the only acceptable norm. Being introverted simply means that a person likes to be on their own sometimes, in order to “process” their thoughts and emotions. It’s like a time to recharge for them. It’s the exact opposite of how extroverts are, who feed on the energy of others—they simply need to constantly engage with other people in some form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-2&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout her book, Cain presents the extroverts and introverts as polar opposites, but as opposites that need to work well together. It’s the balance of the two types of personalities that brings out the best from each of them. But at the same time, she gives a voice to all the introverted people and presents us exactly how we are. We prefer to listen more and talk less, we hate small talk but enjoy deep discussions, we dislike conflict. And that’s perfectly fine. Just because being an introvert is being a part of a minority it doesn’t mean that we should all act as extroverts, just because it’s the social norm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/photo/17204619-quiet&quot;&gt;Quiet on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;originals&quot;&gt;Originals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1534874989l/31341887._SY475_.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Originals by Adam Grant&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Originals by Adam Grant &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book got my attention because of its attractive cover, I must admit. Then, one day, I saw Adam Grant’s Ted Talk and found it insightful. I’d recognised that I had his book on my “to-read” list for a while so I decided to finally read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-3&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’m glad I did. Grant’s writing is simple but compelling. He backs his arguments with research and tells awesome stories at the same time. His book includes examples of Steve Jobs’ and other’s famous entrepreneurs’ greatest failure when they invested into Segway, why the TV show Seinfeld almost didn’t make it and how he himself failed to invest into a company that seemed to be doomed but turned out to be a huge success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-3&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant argues that in order to be original you need to be involved with many different things (read: hobbies), you need to produce huge amounts of work, you don’t need to be the first to come up with an idea (known as first mover’s advantage) and also that collaboration is overrated. His book drives to insightful conclusions and actionable things a reader can do to be more “original”. But at the same time: our originality needs to be presented to others in a way that they find acceptable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If it’s not original enough, it’s boring or trite. If it’s too original, it may be hard for the audience to understand. The goal is to push the envelope, not tear the envelope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/31341887-originals&quot;&gt;Originals on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rest&quot;&gt;Rest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight img-border&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://i.gr-assets.com/images/S/compressed.photo.goodreads.com/books/1525183689l/36342157.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rest by Alex Soojung-Kim Pang&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Rest by Alex Soojung-Kim Pang &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Productivity is one of my favourite topics. Cal Newport already mentioned the importance of rest in his book &lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt; but didn’t go into details. I’m really glad that Alex Soojung-Kim Pang did. Knowing what I did from Newport’s ideas, I felt attracted to the subtitle of Pang’s book when I saw it in a bookshop: &lt;em&gt;Why you get more done when you work less.&lt;/em&gt; It sounds counter-intuitive, I know, but as I was already familiar with the concept, I wanted to explore further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-4&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, it’s my favourite style of writing—a combination of story-telling and backed by research. I loved it because it touches on the other great problem I think we have as a society—working too hard. I experienced working 13 hours a day when I freelanced alongside my full-time job. I had no hobbies, didn’t work on anything out of my own interest so my life was boring and meaningless. Unfortunately, this description would fit the lives of millions of people around the world. Overworking is becoming the norm. Pang puts it perfectly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Today’s leaders treat stress and overwork as a badge of honour, brag about how little they sleep and how few vacation days they take…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-take-away&quot;&gt;Key take away&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pang argues that &lt;em&gt;when we stop and rest properly, we’re not paying tax on creativity, we’re investing in it.&lt;/em&gt; He presents work and rest as two sides of the same coin and argues that they need to be in balance. But by “rest” he doesn’t mean lying on the couch doing nothing (although even this form of rest is needed sometimes), he advocates for an active approach of spending free time. But first of all, we need to reshape our lives so that we actually have some free time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your work is your self, when you cease to work, you cease to exist.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Alex Soojung-Kim Pang&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on and describes (and backs with research) how working fewer hours per day, having a morning routine, taking walks and naps as well as sleeping well stimulates our creativity. I adopted some of the things he suggests in the book and found that they had a profoundly positive impact on my life. Years ago, I used to burn out every couple of months, now I’m able to sustain high productivity and efficiency by resting more and working less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/36342157-rest&quot;&gt;Rest on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for 2019. My favourite five books and how they shaped me and my life. I hope this post gives you a couple of ideas for what to read next, maybe you’ll benefit from these books as much as I did. I certainly hope so.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Books" /><category term="Business" /><category term="Entrepreneurship" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Would you do your job for free?</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/10/16/would-you-do-your-job-for-free/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Would you do your job for free?" /><published>2019-10-16T21:56:54+02:00</published><updated>2019-10-16T21:56:54+02:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/10/16/would-you-do-your-job-for-free</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/10/16/would-you-do-your-job-for-free/">&lt;p&gt;I remember telling this to the CEO of the first company that hired me as a full-time UX designer: “thanks for the raise but it really isn’t about money for me. If I could, I’d do this for free.” They were really happy with my performance so they gave me a raise just a couple of months after I started working there. Until then, I had a full-time, non-designer job which I hated and I freelanced doing design work on the side. Being able to do it full-time literally was a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remembered this a few days ago. That moment was fundamental because I realised I really did love being a designer. But there’s another part to happiness at work that’s equally important—to love working for the company you work for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/search.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Finding the right company to work for is as hard as finding a life partner.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Finding the right company to work for is as hard as finding a life partner. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you launched a product with a subscription of $10 per month. It’s just you who works on the product so you don’t need to share your profits with anyone. You own the house you live in and you only need to cover your costs of living—food and utility bills. Let’s say that the total of your costs of living is $1,000 per month. In two months, 1,000 people sign up for your product. Your costs of running the product are marginal (server/hosting and other smaller fees). This means you’re getting $10,000 in every month and only $1,000 out. You have a profit of around $9,000 per month. That’s more than $100,000 per year and should be more than enough to support a normal lifestyle for a typical family. &lt;em&gt;Would you keep your job?&lt;/em&gt; If no, &lt;em&gt;would you still contribute to the solution your company works on?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Loving what you do and the company you work for leads to meaningful work which leads to personal fulfilment.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you answered yes to the first question, you probably love doing what you do. It’s not so much about the money it brings, it’s more about the happiness it brings you while you work on the things you want to work on. If you answered “no”, then the opposite is probably true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you answered yes to the second question, then that probably means that you also love working for the company you’re working for. This is the hardest part in working for others—it’s hard to find a company that aligns with your values and goals. You may enjoy being a designer but you don’t truly love working for the company that you do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I love being a designer, it’s all I ever wanted to be. I love it so much that I can’t simply stop working at 5pm. But working for my employer for more than 8 hours a day would hurt my productivity and would also be against my values. So I work on my personal projects. Again, it’s not because I have to work on them but because I want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work for GitLab—an all-remote company with values that aren’t just a couple of words on a website. It’s a company that grew from an OpenSource project and established its values as it went. They aren’t something that a bunch of clueless directors came up with on an off-site event. That, combined with the fact that these values are well-aligned with what I look for from an employer, makes me think that I’d continue contributing to GitLab even if I left the company someday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ux-buddy&quot;&gt;UX Buddy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to put in words how glad I am to have found something I love doing in my life and a company that I love working for. It’s been a tough journey, one of the ups and downs and learning from my mistakes, but it eventually led me to where I wanted to get. I can’t really help others with the first question (do you love doing what you do?), but I can help with the second one. So if you love being a designer but don’t really love working for the company you’re working for, my latest side project might be for you. It’s called UX Buddy and it’s about helping UX and product designers find a better job. A job where they don’t just push pixels, where they don’t just do things they’re told, but actually get to collaborate with others and help drive the company towards solving user problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m doing an early launch for people on my mailing list who can get the course for half price, with a chance of a &lt;em&gt;total 75% discount&lt;/em&gt; 😲 If you love being a designer but don’t love the company you work for or the work you do for them, &lt;a href=&quot;https://uxbuddy.co&quot;&gt;check the UX Buddy course out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX-Buddy" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Work" /><summary type="html">I remember telling this to the CEO of the first company that hired me as a full-time UX designer: “thanks for the raise but it really isn’t about money for me. If I could, I’d do this for free.” They were really happy with my performance so they gave me a raise just a couple of months after I started working there. Until then, I had a full-time, non-designer job which I hated and I freelanced doing design work on the side. Being able to do it full-time literally was a dream come true.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Open-plan offices are the sweatshops of the West</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open-plan offices are the sweatshops of the West" /><published>2019-02-01T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west/">&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, I joined a tiny startup and it was the first time I experienced an open-plan office. There were only three other people working with me in that office and we really got along. We went to lunch together, took walks together, hung out in our free time and built a friendly relationship based on trust. My journey would then take me forward to London where I’d end up working for other, larger startups. Little did I know, that the tiny Luxembourgish company would be the only positive onsite working environment that I’d get to experience in my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“No nesting!”, I’m told. I’m expected to move around, sit in different areas each day.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
After working for a medium-sized startup in London I went on to work for an enterprise. The office was the most stylish compared to the previous ones, it was larger and in a recently-built skyscraper just the opposite of the Google headquarters. Beautiful views of downtown London on one side, similar skyscrapers on the other. Long rows of tables everywhere and busy-looking people slouching over their laptops. Lively and even somewhat noisy, but, surprisingly, it all looked strangely bleak. I learned on the first day that the company practices what they call “a clean desk policy”. This simply means that at the end of the day you need to pack your shit up, put it in a box and take it to your little American-high-school-looking locker. “No nesting!”, I’m told. I’m expected to move around, sit in different areas each day. It’s supposed to make me interact with different people in the company.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-plan-offices-done-wrong&quot;&gt;Open-plan offices done wrong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporations like these try to emulate the startup working environment by creating such open offices where they throw 100 people in and tell them to collaborate. They expect cross-pollination of ideas like we’re fucking bees or something. It’s not that simple. It kinda works for startups because the teams are usually really small. We’re talking about 5 to 7 people. Collaborating in an open-plan office is great when everyone is working on the same thing, when you’re all on the same mission, when you hang out with them during lunch time, go home together… But when you share your space with people who work on different things (sometimes even in different departments) that constantly distract you with their noisiness &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; nosiness it’s a completely different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;full-bleed-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/open-office.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A typical open-plan office. Endless rows of desks, people slouching over laptops with zero privacy and maximum distractions.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A typical open-plan office. Endless rows of desks, people slouching over laptops with zero privacy and maximum distractions. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/QBpZGqEMsKg&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what large companies that try to emulate startups get wrong the most. And the worst thing about it is that they &lt;em&gt;don’t even realise that they’re not getting it&lt;/em&gt;. They just brag about their “&lt;em&gt;cool office&lt;/em&gt;” and how “&lt;em&gt;we’re all about collaboration&lt;/em&gt;” and “&lt;em&gt;flat hierarchy&lt;/em&gt;”. They think that a cool office will create a great culture. That cleaning up your own desk everyday will force you to sit with Jeff from the sales department and get friendly with him to eventually share ideas and interests. Well, let me tell you something: Jeff is fucking annoying and I, as an introverted designer, have absolutely nothing in common with him. He’s nothing but a huge distraction to me. I can still hear him yap around on his call even through my headphones playing the loudest Death Metal music I can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaboration-kills-creativity&quot;&gt;Collaboration kills creativity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was an interesting study called &lt;em&gt;Coding War Games&lt;/em&gt; conducted by Tom Demarco which compared 600 computer programmers at 92 companies. Long story short, they found:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;that people from the same companies performed at roughly the same level — but that there was an enormous performance gap between organizations. What distinguished programmers at the top-performing companies wasn’t greater experience or better pay. It was how much privacy, personal workspace and freedom from interruption they enjoyed. &lt;em&gt;Sixty-two percent of the best performers said their workspace was sufficiently private compared with only 19 percent of the worst performers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There it is: &lt;em&gt;privacy, personal workspace&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;freedom from interruption&lt;/em&gt;. These are the things that make programmers produce better work, not experience or higher salary. But it seems most companies rather &lt;em&gt;spend&lt;/em&gt; money hiring highly experienced programmers, pay them high salaries and have them produce mediocre work because they want to &lt;em&gt;save&lt;/em&gt; money on the office costs. Mindblowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to make the open-plan office work in larger companies would be to keep some walls between sections that divide the office into small working areas where people feel safe and, most of all, comfortable. To create small offices for teams of 5 to 7 people (who work on the same thing/project) where they can collaborate and work undisturbed. Some companies, including Facebook which was the largest advocate for open-plan offices, are starting to revert to something like that. I guess they finally figured out that open-plan offices don’t actually work. And there’s solid research to back that claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-plan-offices-simply-dont-work&quot;&gt;Open-plan offices simply don’t work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the open-plan offices is to encourage collaboration, increase transparency, improve efficiency, and establish a great working relationship between the workers. To quote one of the loudest advocates of open-plan offices, Jack Dorsey, co-founder of Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We encourage people to stay out in the open because we believe in serendipity—and people walking by each other teaching new things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the small offices that are reserved for meetings and calls in these kinds of environments are usually surrounded by transparent walls. So even when you’re trying to isolate yourself a bit, everyone can still see you. I guess it’s all in the name of transparency. Collaboration, transparency, efficiency and friendship at work all sounds nice, but is there any research backing this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s research alright, but it’s not backing the claims of the open-plan office advocates. In fact, it proves the opposite. Researches at Harvard found that after switching to an open-plan office:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Overall, face-to-face time decreased by around 70 percent across the participating employees, on average, with email use increasing by between 22 percent and 50 percent…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experienced this myself. I’ve seen people who were sitting opposite of each other communicating through chat messages. All day long. Interestingly, both were wearing noise-cancelling headphones. When I saw that, I felt that it was something that’s perfectly fine to do and adopted it. Another study found that:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…many workers in open offices are frustrated by distractions that lead to poorer work performance. Nearly half of the surveyed workers in open offices said the lack of sound privacy was a significant problem for them and more than 30 percent complained about the lack of visual privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…the loss of productivity due to noise distraction … was doubled in open-plan offices compared to private offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This answers &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I always felt so anxious in these types of offices. Being an introvert, I found it extremely hard to isolate myself in such noisy environments. Especially because they’re noisy in a bad way. It’s not the same as working in a coffee shop where everything blends into the background. And then here’s the final nail in the coffin for the open-plan offices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While employees feel like they’re part of a laid-back, innovative enterprise, the environment ultimately damages workers’ attention spans, productivity, creative thinking, and satisfaction.  Furthermore, a sense of privacy boosts job performance, while the opposite can cause feelings of helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so if research proves that open-plan offices don’t work, why are 80% of office working environments already open-plan? The amount of space per employee shrank from 50 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in 1970 to less than 20 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in 2010&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Switching to an open-plan office is a global trend. Why do companies increasingly keep switching to it if it doesn’t actually work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-sweatshops-of-the-west&quot;&gt;The new sweatshops of the west&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look with horror at the typical sweatshops in Asia that, whether we like it or not, produce most of the products we buy. Rooms, crowded with people (and sometimes children) with no private space, trying to focus in such distracting and sometimes hazardous environment. Trying their best to produce the amount of work that will guarantee them their daily wage. Bad lighting, poor quality of air, limited toilet time, limited breaks. In short, extremely poor and unacceptable working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aren’t the open-plan offices similar? People sitting in rows of desks with very limited space, no privacy, trying their best but can’t focus because of the many distractions? Isn’t this similar to a sweatshop but with better working conditions? Yes, the offices look nice and stylish, there’s air conditioning, decent lighting and good-enough office equipment—most office workers don’t have access to ergonomic office equipment—but at closer inspection, it’s just a nicer sweatshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it from the employer’s perspective. An office in central London is extremely expensive. The best way to make use of it is to turn it into an open-plan office and fill it with as many people as possible. Give them perks to distract them from those feelings of unproductiveness, anxiousness and even helplessness, that research suggests they have. Sweatshops were a thing in the west one hundred years ago but it seems they’re making a come back only in a nicer, stylish form. Open-plan offices are nothing more than a sweatshop disguised as “environments that promote collaboration, transparency, [insert a bullshit corporate term here]…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sweatshop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Different time period, worse working conditions, but the concept is the same.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Different time period, worse working conditions, but the concept is the same. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweatshop#/media/File:Millville,_New_Jersey_-_Dresses._Second_view_of_the_Western_Dress_Factory._Emphasis_on_general_conditions_in_the..._-_NARA_-_518630.jpg&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journey through all this led me to a simple conclusion. I was my best self, most productive and most sane when I worked from home. That’s why after 5 years of distracting environments, limited efficiency, anxiety, helplessness and lack of control, I decided to &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely/&quot;&gt;go back to working remotely&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why An Open Office Environment Can Totally Kill Creativity&lt;/em&gt; by Aimee Groth (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/why-an-open-office-environment-can-totally-kill-creativity-2012-1?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Harvard Study: Your Open-Plan Office Is Making Your Team Less Collaborative&lt;/em&gt; by Jessica Stillman (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/jessica-stillman/new-harvard-study-you-open-plan-office-is-making-your-team-less-collaborative.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Google got it wrong. The open-office trend is destroying the workplace.&lt;/em&gt; by Lindsey Kaufman (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2014/12/30/google-got-it-wrong-the-open-office-trend-is-destroying-the-workplace/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.aaaabe89c4ba&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quiet. The power of Introverts in a World That Can’t Stop Talking&lt;/em&gt; by Susan Cain (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17204619-quiet&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Remote" /><category term="Psychology" /><category term="Work" /><summary type="html">Six years ago, I joined a tiny startup and it was the first time I experienced an open-plan office. There were only three other people working with me in that office and we really got along. We went to lunch together, took walks together, hung out in our free time and built a friendly relationship based on trust. My journey would then take me forward to London where I’d end up working for other, larger startups. Little did I know, that the tiny Luxembourgish company would be the only positive onsite working environment that I’d get to experience in my career.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My favourite books of 2018</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My favourite books of 2018" /><published>2019-01-18T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2019-01-18T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018/">&lt;p&gt;Similarly to &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017/&quot;&gt;last year’s favourite books of 2017&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to write a quick blog post about some of my favourite books that I read in 2018. Out of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/11006629-matej-latin?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;shelf=read&amp;amp;title=matej-latin&amp;amp;sort=date_read&amp;amp;order=d&quot;&gt;the 19 that I managed to read&lt;/a&gt; (exactly the same number as in 2017), here are my top 5. Keep in mind these are books I read in 2018, not necessarily released in 2018 and they’re not sorted in any particular order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utopia-for-realists&quot;&gt;Utopia for realists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1488137159l/34400335.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Rutger Bregman&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Rutger Bregman &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received this book as a Christmas gift. It had been on my to-read list for a while but to be honest, the thing that attracted me the most about it was its cover. I know we shouldn’t &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2016/07/21/judging-books/&quot;&gt;judge books by their covers&lt;/a&gt; but I feel that as a designer, I’m even more susceptible to this. If I see a book with cool typography on its cover, I’ll check it out. That’s how this book got into my to-read list in the first place. I liked the cover, checked what it was about, found it interesting and added it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually don’t like to talk or write about politics. I find it very divisive. But every now and then, I do enjoy a book about it. This was one of them. I think my perception of this book was affected by The Rational Optimist which I had read just one month earlier. Rutger Bregman, the author, argues that despite the stupendous progress in the last two centuries (measured by life expectancy and per capita income) there hasn’t been a change in quality of life accompanying it. In fact, poverty is still a huge problem, so is our work-life balance. We work more to be able to afford less compared to the generations before ours. We were promised advent of robots would eliminate boring and repetitive jobs, reduce our weekly working hours and enable us to live fuller and happier lives. Instead, the opposite is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rutger, also explores relatively radical ideas like giving free money to everyone, reduce our working hours to 15-a-week and introduce basic income. His case is compelling as he provides research backing these ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems we take the world around us for granted. Get up, commute to work, spend 8-10 hours in an uninspiring working environment, doing dull and boring work, only to spend another hour commuting back home, completely exhausted. I lived that life back in London and I did something about it. I think it’s time we start doing something about it collectively. Irrational exhaustion of human resources needs to stop and there are many ways to go about it (remote work which eliminates the need for commuting for example). But it seems we’re not ready yet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Discontent”, said Oscar Wilde, “is the first step in the progress of a man or a nation”.&lt;br /&gt;
—Rutger Bregman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was discontent about my life when it was what everyone would regard as normal. &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely/&quot;&gt;Going back to working remotely&lt;/a&gt; improved it drastically for me. But that may not be an option for everyone. And as long as the masses of workers don’t feel discontent about it, our qualities of life won’t improve on the nation-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34400335-utopia-for-realists&quot;&gt;Utopia for Realists on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;influence&quot;&gt;Influence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1391026083l/28815.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Robert B. Cialdini&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Robert B. Cialdini &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the many books that I read about how our brains work in the decision-making process, Thinking Fast and Slow and How We Decide are two more. I read all three of them in 2018 but this one stood out the most. I think it must be the balance between the length of the content, the language used and the slick storytelling—something that the other two failed at. How We Decide was very well told and articulated through stories, while Thinking Fast and Slow was very condensed, with long chapters and sometimes seemingly unnecessary details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-1&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three tell a similar story: we make decisions that are based on rationality or our emotions. We like to think that we’re in control of our decisions but we’re not. Completely different parts of our brains activate when taking different kind of decisions. The emotional part is the fast-thinking and the rational is the slower. But the tricky part is that we need both: emotional fast-thinking based on past experiences and urges keeps us alive in unexpected situations, the rational slow-thinking part allows us to solve complex problems. Influence is based on numerous psychological research and gives concrete, real-life examples of how to make better decisions and how certain entities (corporations) abuse this knowledge and trick us into buying the more expensive product or buy even what we don’t really need because &lt;em&gt;there are only x items left&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-1&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re not the rational beings we assume we are, and we’re easily tricked into doing things against our benefits on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28815.Influence&quot;&gt;Influence on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deep-work&quot;&gt;Deep work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1451409702l/28383248.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Cal Newport&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Cal Newport &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book was also on my to-read list for a while. I believe I added because someone recommended it but I never took the time to take a closer look and see what exactly it’s about. In April last year, I moved from London to Edinburgh and started working remotely for GitLab. I had worked remotely before but it was never a full-time position with a remote-only company. I didn’t know what exactly to expect but I knew I wanted to organise my working days better. Especially compared to my days back in London. I remembered of this book and decided to read it. I have been recommending it to all my remotely-working colleagues ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-2&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will depend on the type of person you are: you either like flexible working hours and work whenever you have time and “feel like it” or you need somewhat rigid frames to be productive. I’m the latter. If I don’t have structure, I waste time. I procrastinate, keep putting work off until it’s urgent. The worst thing is that in the end, I feel really bad about not being productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out there’s shallow work and then there’s deep work. Shallow work is when we’re busy working but keep switching between tasks, emails, Slack chat etc. We’re working, but we’re not productive. Deep work is the opposite. When we work deeply, we focus on one task, eliminate distractions and concentrate. Deep work is essential for any type of work creatives or technical people do (designers and developers). It’s really important to block out hours of time for deep work. Intervals of 2-3 hours work best. After reading this book, I reorganised my working days and also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2018/05/17/remote-work-eliminate-distractions-getting-things-done/&quot;&gt;Eliminating distractions and getting things done&lt;/a&gt;  to document my process and help others do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-2&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocking out time, reserved for focus is essential for deep work. And deep work is the most productive and effective way to solve complex problems or produce slick solutions. Take a look at how you spend your time. Track it for a couple of days if necessary. This will give you a great overview and you’ll be able to find room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28383248-deep-work&quot;&gt;Deep Work on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disrupted&quot;&gt;Disrupted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471657959l/29744770.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Dan Lyons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Dan Lyons &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funny thing. I don’t think I would ever read this book if it wasn’t on sale on Amazon for £0.95 and didn’t have a cool cover that attracted me immediately. I had no idea what to expect, I first thought it was a book about startups and how they disrupt markets with innovative products. It’s not. It’s about a journalist who loses his job as an editor of a popular magazine/website and joins a local startup. Reading this book felt like reading his journal about his experiences while working for this startup company—HubSpot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-3&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever worked for a startup with a “strong culture” and felt a bit weird or unfitting, you’ll identify with a lot of what Dan Lyons, the author, went through. He writes about typical startup bullshit: big promises that lead to disappointments, social pressures to fit in with “the culture” (or what I sometimes describe as “the cult”), the internal politics and about the coming to a realisation of what most of these startups are—money making machines  fuelled by hype. The more hype they manage to produce, the more millions the founders make. For most of these companies it’s not even about creating a useful product for the users, but more about “cashing in”. I went through similar experiences of trying to fit in with a “startup cult” and connected with the author on several points. &lt;em&gt;A hilarious and amusing read if you ever worked for a startup.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-3&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Startup jobs are exciting. The possibility of joining a small but growing company with great potential is very tempting. The problem is that most of these startups turn into something resembling cults. You either fit in or not. And this will be the biggest factor in how successful your time with that company will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29744770-disrupted&quot;&gt;Disrupted on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-daily-stoic&quot;&gt;The Daily stoic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1462161080l/29093292.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Ryan Holiday&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Ryan Holiday &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a book that I started reading in August 2017. It’s a book with 366 meditations and the reader is supposed to read one each day. Some go on and read more but I believe they miss the point of the book. The point is to adopt the stoic mentality one step at a time. It works really well if you establish a routine of reading the daily thought regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-4&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that each book I read changes me. It changes me the way I think as well as how I see the world and my role in it. Sometimes reading a book is merely about learning something new. I think that this book has changed me most profoundly from all the books that I read. It helped me understand the anger that I used to have about pretty much everything. By understanding it and where it came from, I was able to address it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the thoughts in the book are from the writings by Seneca—a Roman stoic philosopher—and Marcus Aurelius—the Roman emperor. The main point of stoicism is to not worry about things that are outside of your control and focus on the things that you &lt;strong&gt;can control&lt;/strong&gt;. This book has helped me make decisions that I would never be able to make without realising that. I keep reading the meditations every day even though I already read the whole book. I think I’ll keep reading them for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-take-away&quot;&gt;Key take away&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unhappiness in our lives is often triggered by the things outside of our control. This is especially true in our world driven by capitalism where we’re constantly pushed to be better than others, have more of everything and be perceived by everyone else as great and our lives as worthy of envy. If we’re content with what we have and not always yearn for more, we can actually achieve happiness. Unlike most things, our desires &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; under our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Control your perceptions.&lt;br /&gt;
Direct your actions properly.&lt;br /&gt;
Willingly accept what’s outside your control.&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all we need to do.&lt;br /&gt;
—Ryan Holiday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds simple, but it takes conscious effort every day to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29093292-the-daily-stoic&quot;&gt;The Daily Stoic on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it. These are my favourite 5 books of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/11006629-matej-latin?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;shelf=read&amp;amp;title=matej-latin&amp;amp;sort=date_read&amp;amp;order=d&quot;&gt;19 that I read this year&lt;/a&gt;. I hope that I gave you a few ideas on what to read next. What’s a cool book that you read this year? Can’t wait to see your recommendations in the comments below. :yum:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Books" /><category term="Psychology" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">Similarly to last year’s favourite books of 2017, I wanted to write a quick blog post about some of my favourite books that I read in 2018. Out of the 19 that I managed to read (exactly the same number as in 2017), here are my top 5. Keep in mind these are books I read in 2018, not necessarily released in 2018 and they’re not sorted in any particular order.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2 questions we ask designers in job interviews</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/10/25/2-questions-we-ask-designers-and-why/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2 questions we ask designers in job interviews" /><published>2018-10-25T21:56:54+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-25T21:56:54+02:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/10/25/2-questions-we-ask-designers-and-why</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/10/25/2-questions-we-ask-designers-and-why/">&lt;p&gt;We won’t ask you how many golf balls fit in a bus or how many times a day a clock’s hands overlap – nothing like what Google became famous for. While there’s some value in seeing how candidates react to curve-ball questions, they don’t really add much to a 45-minute interview. We also won’t ask you to attend an all-day session with a series of interviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/job-families/engineering/ux-designer/#hiring-process&quot;&gt;hiring process&lt;/a&gt; at GitLab is way simpler and more efficient. A successful candidate has to go through four stages of interviewing before receiving an offer. Altogether, we spend around 2-3 hours with them, so we need to ask the right questions to be efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so confident in the efficiency of these questions that I’m completely okay with sharing these publicly. &lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; you answer matters less than &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you answer them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the GitLab blog, &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/2018/10/25/two-questions-we-ask-ux-designers-in-job-interviews/&quot;&gt;read the full story here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Design" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">We won’t ask you how many golf balls fit in a bus or how many times a day a clock’s hands overlap – nothing like what Google became famous for. While there’s some value in seeing how candidates react to curve-ball questions, they don’t really add much to a 45-minute interview. We also won’t ask you to attend an all-day session with a series of interviewers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buzz junkie</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buzz junkie" /><published>2018-08-27T11:56:54+02:00</published><updated>2018-08-27T11:56:54+02:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie/">&lt;p&gt;It’s early in the morning, probably around 7 because it’s still quite dark outside. I’m reading a book and trying to relax a bit before another busy day, my phone is resting on the table not too far away from me, but still out of reach. The book is about stoicism and a lot of topics in it are about having control over our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indent&quot;&gt;“Buzzz, buzzz!” The phone suddenly comes to life with vibrating sounds and light emitting from the screen that turns on. As it does, it slightly illuminates the dark room with its blueish glow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  

  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/smartphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by Andrew Guan&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by Andrew Guan &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wave of emotions hits me. Excitement, mixed with a bit of fear and anticipation—is it someone who needs my help? Someone from my subscribers telling me about their story? Is it someone sending me feedback about my book? I jump from my armchair and frantically rush to press the button to turn the screen back on. The moments seem like minutes before I finally get to see what the notifications is. It’s Twitter. “Rob White just liked a photo by Hung Lee…” What?! Who the fuck are these people and why the fuck should I care? You disturbed my morning routine, made me get up from the chair, destroyed my focus, made me feel anxious and interrupted me while reading the book and this is what I get in return?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What?! Who the fuck are these people and why the fuck should I&amp;nbsp;care?&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
I used to take my phone everywhere with me—always in my side pocket. I would jump on it like a starved lion jumps on a fresh piece of meat whenever it buzzed. I would check in on it even when it didn’t buzz. Shit, sometimes I would even check it a couple of times in a single minute. I always expected something important and meaningful to show up on that screen but most of the time, the screen was either full of junk or worse—empty. When it was empty I would go on and unlock the phone and start checking in on every app that I commonly used. &lt;em&gt;There’s gotta be something there but the notification probably didn’t come through&lt;/em&gt;, is what I was thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been doing that for years and never saw anything wrong with it but then one day it hit me. I looked at myself from the third person. Jumping from whatever I was doing just to check the phone. Checking in even when it didn’t buzz. I was pathetic. Like a junkie, dependant on that dopamine rush but only to be let down every time. Like a mouse in an experiment not knowing what the sound brings, food or an electric shock. Like the people in casinos, putting the coins into the machine and pulling the lever always expecting that this time it will really be their time. This time they’ll hit the jackpot and become rich. But they never do. I wasn’t any better, I was a buzz junkie. Hooked to the meaninglessness of social media. How could I have been tricked into becoming such a fool? Why did I allow these corporations to come in and disrupt my personal life like that? Why did I allow to feel nervous and agitated all the time because of this shit? It brings no value to me. Absolutely zero. So why keep doing it? At that moment, I found it ironic that I had been reading a book about stoicism and having control over my life for almost a year but only realised that so late. I had very little control over my life and I needed to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breaking-a-habit&quot;&gt;Breaking a habit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did, I disabled all notifications except messages. I never had the Facebook app on my phone and now it was time to delete a few more. I always used the ‘Do not disturb’ mode that comes with iOS and set it from 10 pm to 7 am. I go to sleep at 10 in the evening and get up at 6 in the morning so that meant I only had one hour of distraction-free time. That’s crazy, why would I allow meaningless shit to agitate me right before I go to sleep? Why would I want to start my day with this meaningless shit? I changed the ‘Do not disturb’ mode to start at 8 pm and end at 9 am. Now nobody can disturb and agitate me two hours before I go to sleep and 3 hours after I wake up. This had a tremendous effect on not feeling anxious all the time. I feel more relaxed in general, I don’t look for meaningless distractions, I can focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I feel more relaxed in general, I don’t look for meaningless distractions, I can focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
It took some time to get used to these changes. Occasionally, I still felt the urge to check on my phone and I had to make a conscious decision to stop myself from doing it. It &lt;em&gt;needs to be a&lt;/em&gt; conscious decision until we get used to it, it’s the only way to rewire our brain. I still get that urge sometimes when I glance at my phone lying somewhere, just waiting for me to turn the screen on and see what cool things it has in store for me. Most times I manage to resist the urge, sometimes I give in. It takes a long time to break a habit. But breaking a bad habit is liberating and worth the effort. I don’t feel as anxious and constantly agitated anymore. I feel I finally have peace of mind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to feel sorry for people that are hooked on drugs… but aren’t we all hooked on something? It can be as innocent as sugar and coffee or something more destructive—cigarettes, social media… How do you use your phone? What is your relationship with social media like? &lt;a href=&quot;#comments&quot;&gt;Comment bellow&lt;/a&gt; because I’d love to hear your stories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">It’s early in the morning, probably around 7 because it’s still quite dark outside. I’m reading a book and trying to relax a bit before another busy day, my phone is resting on the table not too far away from me, but still out of reach. The book is about stoicism and a lot of topics in it are about having control over our lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Standups suck, and here’s how to fix them</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/06/03/standups-suck/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Standups suck, and here’s how to fix them" /><published>2018-06-03T21:56:54+02:00</published><updated>2018-06-03T21:56:54+02:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/06/03/standups-suck</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/06/03/standups-suck/">&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    This is how my usual mornings went.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d get to the office at around 8:30 am—a bit early so I had some time to sort out my desk and check email. My first standup was at 9:20 am. This was the design standup which should have taken about 10 minutes but quite often extended to double its allocated time. I then had 20 minutes till the next standup at 10 am. This was the one that always started late and usually extended well over the allocated time. Right after that one, at 10:15 am was the next standup. This one usually took about 15 minutes to get through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for Mind the Product and you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/2018/05/standups-suck-and-heres-how-to-fix-them/&quot;&gt;read the full story here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">This is how my usual mornings went.</summary></entry></feed>