<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-02T17:51:55+00:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Matej Latin</title><subtitle>Matej Latin is a Senior UX designer at GitLab and is based in Edinburgh, UK. He writes about design, minimalism and typography.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Open-plan offices are the sweatshops of the west</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Open-plan offices are the sweatshops of the west" /><published>2019-02-01T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2019-02-01T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/02/01/open-plan-offices-are-the-sweatshops-of-the-west/">&lt;p&gt;Six years ago, I joined a tiny startup and it was the first time I experienced an open-plan office. There were only three other people working with me in that office and we really got along. We went to lunch together, took walks together, hung out in our free time and built a friendly relationship based on trust. My journey would then take me forward to London where I’d end up working for other, larger startups. Little did I know, that the tiny Luxembourgish company would be the only positive onsite working environment that I’d get to experience in my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“No nesting!”, I’m told. I’m expected to move around, sit in different areas each day.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
After working for a medium-sized startup in London I went on to work for an enterprise. The office was the most stylish compared to the previous ones, it was larger and in a recently-built skyscraper just the opposite of the Google headquarters. Beautiful views of downtown London on one side, similar skyscrapers on the other. Long rows of tables everywhere and busy-looking people slouching over their laptops. Lively and even somewhat noisy, but, surprisingly, it all looked strangely bleak. I learned on the first day that the company practices what they call “a clean desk policy”. This simply means that at the end of the day you need to pack your shit up, put it in a box and take it to your little American-high-school-looking locker. “No nesting!”, I’m told. I’m expected to move around, sit in different areas each day. It’s supposed to make me interact with different people in the company. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-plan-offices-done-wrong&quot;&gt;Open-plan offices done wrong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corporations like these try to emulate the startup working environment by creating such open offices where they throw 100 people in, and tell them to collaborate. They expect cross-pollination of ideas like we’re fucking bees or something. It’s not that simple. It kinda works for startups because the teams are usually really small. We’re talking about 5 to 7 people. Collaborating in an open office is great when everyone is working on the same thing, when you’re all on the same mission, when you hang out with them during lunch time, go home together… But when you share your space with people who work on different things (sometimes even in different departments) and constantly distract you with their noisiness &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; nosiness it’s a completely different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;full-bleed-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/open-office.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A typical open-plan office. Endless rows of desks, people slouching over laptops with zero privacy and maximum distractions.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A typical open-plan office. Endless rows of desks, people slouching over laptops with zero privacy and maximum distractions. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/photos/QBpZGqEMsKg&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what large companies that try to emulate startups get wrong the most. And the worst thing about it, is that they &lt;em&gt;don’t even realise that they’re not getting it&lt;/em&gt;. The just brag about their “&lt;em&gt;cool office&lt;/em&gt;” and how “&lt;em&gt;we’re all about collaboration&lt;/em&gt;” and “&lt;em&gt;flat hierarchy&lt;/em&gt;”. They think that a cool office will create a great culture. That cleaning up your own desk everyday will force you to sit with Jeff from the sales department and get friendly with him to eventually share ideas and interests. Well, let me tell you something: Jeff is fucking annoying and I, as an introverted designer, have absolutely nothing in common with him. He’s nothing but a huge distraction to me. I can still hear him yap around on his call even through my headphones playing the loudest Death Metal music I can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaboration-kills-creativity&quot;&gt;Collaboration kills creativity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was an interesting study called &lt;em&gt;Coding War Games&lt;/em&gt; conducted by Tom Demarco which compared 600 computer programmers at 92 companies. Long story short, they found:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;that people from the same companies performed at roughly the same level — but that there was an enormous performance gap between organizations. What distinguished programmers at the top-performing companies wasn’t greater experience or better pay. It was how much privacy, personal workspace and freedom from interruption they enjoyed. &lt;em&gt;Sixty-two percent of the best performers said their workspace was sufficiently private compared with only 19 percent of the worst performers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There it is: &lt;em&gt;privacy, personal workspace&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;freedom from interruption&lt;/em&gt;. These are the things that make programmers produce better work, not experience or higher salary. But it seems most companies rather &lt;em&gt;spend&lt;/em&gt; money hiring highly experienced programmers, pay them high salaries and have them produce mediocre work because they want to &lt;em&gt;save&lt;/em&gt; money on the office than the other way around. Mindblowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only way to make the open-plan office work in larger companies would be to keep some walls between sections that divide the office into small working areas where people feel safe and, most of all, comfortable. To create small offices for teams of 5 to 7 people (who work on the same thing/project) where they can collaborate and work undisturbed. Some companies, including Facebook which was the largest advocate for open-plan offices, are starting to revert to something like that. I guess they finally figured out that open-plan offices don’t actually work. And there’s solid research to back that claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;open-plan-offices-simply-dont-work&quot;&gt;Open-plan offices simply don’t work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the open-plan offices is to encourage collaboration, increase transparency, improve efficiency, and establish a great working relationship between the workers. To quote one of the loudest advocates of open-plan offices, Jack Dorsey, co-founder of Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We encourage people to stay out in the open because we believe in serendipity—and people walking by each other teaching new things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the small offices that are reserved for meetings and calls in these kinds of environments are usually surrounded with transparent walls. So even when you’re trying to isolate yourself a bit, everyone can still see you. I guess it’s all in the name of transparency. Collaboration, transparency, efficiency and friendship at work all sounds nice, but is there any research backing this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s research alright, but it’s not backing the claims of the open-plan office advocates. In fact, it proves the opposite. Researches at Harvard found that after switching to an open-plan office:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Overall, face-to-face time decreased by around 70 percent across the participating employees, on average, with email use increasing by between 22 percent and 50 percent…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I experienced this myself. I’ve seen people who were sitting opposite of each other communicating through chat messages. All day long. Interestingly, both were wearing noise-cancelling headphones. When I saw that, I felt that it was something that’s perfectly fine to do and adopted it. Another study found that:&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…many workers in open offices are frustrated by distractions that lead to poorer work performance. Nearly half of the surveyed workers in open offices said the lack of sound privacy was a significant problem for them and more than 30 percent complained about the lack of visual privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…the loss of productivity due to noise distraction … was doubled in open-plan offices compared to private offices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This answers &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I always felt so anxious in these types of offices. Being an introvert, I found it extremely hard to isolate myself in such noisy environments. Especially because they’re noisy in a bad way. It’s not the same as working in a coffee shop where everything blends into the background. And then here’s the final nail in the coffin for the open-plan offices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;While employees feel like they’re part of a laid-back, innovative enterprise, the environment ultimately damages workers’ attention spans, productivity, creative thinking, and satisfaction.  Furthermore, a sense of privacy boosts job performance, while the opposite can cause feelings of helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so if research proves that open-plan offices don’t work, why are 80% of office working environments already open-plan? The amount of space per employee shrank from 50 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in the 1970 to less than 20 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; in 2010&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Switching to an open-office is a global trend. Why do companies increasingly keep switching to it if it doesn’t actually work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-new-sweatshops-of-the-west&quot;&gt;The new sweatshops of the west&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look with horror at the typical sweatshops in Asia that, whether we like it or not, produce most of the products we buy. Rooms, crowded with people (and sometimes children) with no private space, trying to focus in such distracting and sometimes hazardous environment. Trying their best to produce the amount of work that will guarantee them their daily wage. Bad lighting, poor quality of air, limited toilet time, limited breaks. In short, extremely poor and unacceptable working conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But aren’t the open-plan offices similar? People sitting in rows of desks with very limited space, no privacy, trying their best but can’t focus because of the many distractions? Isn’t this similar to a sweatshop but with better working conditions? Yes, the offices look nice and stylish, there’s air conditioning, decent lighting and good-enough office equipment—most office workers don’t have access to ergonomic office equipment—but at closer inspection, it’s just a nicer sweatshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it from the employer’s perspective. An office in central London is extremely expensive. The best way to make use of it is to turn it into an open-plan office and fill it with as many people as possible. Give them perks to distract them from those feelings of unproductiveness, anxiousness and even helplessness, that research suggests they have. Sweatshops were a thing in the west one hundred years ago but it seems they’re making a come back only in a nicer, stylish form. Open-plan offices are nothing more than a sweatshop disguised as “environments that promote collaboration, transparency, [insert a bullshit corporate term here]…”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sweatshop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Different time period, worse working conditions, but the concept is the same.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Different time period, worse working conditions, but the concept is the same. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sweatshop#/media/File:Millville,_New_Jersey_-_Dresses._Second_view_of_the_Western_Dress_Factory._Emphasis_on_general_conditions_in_the..._-_NARA_-_518630.jpg&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journey through all this led me to a simple conclusion. I was my best self, most productive and most sane when I worked from home. That’s why after 5 years of distracting environments, limited efficiency, anxiety, helplessness and lack of control, I decided to &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely/&quot;&gt;go back to working remotely&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why An Open Office Environment Can Totally Kill Creativity&lt;/em&gt; by Aimee Groth (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/why-an-open-office-environment-can-totally-kill-creativity-2012-1?r=US&amp;amp;IR=T&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Harvard Study: Your Open-Plan Office Is Making Your Team Less Collaborative&lt;/em&gt; by Jessica Stillman (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/jessica-stillman/new-harvard-study-you-open-plan-office-is-making-your-team-less-collaborative.html&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Google got it wrong. The open-office trend is destroying the workplace.&lt;/em&gt; by Lindsey Kaufman (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2014/12/30/google-got-it-wrong-the-open-office-trend-is-destroying-the-workplace/?noredirect=on&amp;amp;utm_term=.aaaabe89c4ba&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quiet. The power of Introverts in a World That Can’t Stop Talking&lt;/em&gt; by Susan Cain (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17204619-quiet&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Remote" /><category term="Psychology" /><summary type="html">Six years ago, I joined a tiny startup and it was the first time I experienced an open-plan office. There were only three other people working with me in that office and we really got along. We went to lunch together, took walks together, hung out in our free time and built a friendly relationship based on trust. My journey would then take me forward to London where I’d end up working for other, larger startups. Little did I know, that the tiny Luxembourgish company would be the only positive onsite working environment that I’d get to experience in my career.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My favourite books of 2018</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My favourite books of 2018" /><published>2019-01-18T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2019-01-18T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2019/01/18/my-favourite-books-of-2018/">&lt;p&gt;Similarly to &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017/&quot;&gt;last year’s favourite books of 2017&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to write a quick blog post about some of my favourite books that I read in 2018. Out of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/11006629-matej-latin?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;shelf=read&amp;amp;title=matej-latin&amp;amp;sort=date_read&amp;amp;order=d&quot;&gt;the 19 that I managed to read&lt;/a&gt; (exactly the same number as in 2017), here are my top 5. Keep in mind these are books I read in 2018, not necessarily released in 2018 and they’re not sorted in any particular order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;utopia-for-realists&quot;&gt;Utopia for realists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1488137159l/34400335.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Rutger Bregman&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Rutger Bregman &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I received this book as a Christmas gift. It had been on my to-read list for a while but to be honest, the thing that attracted me the most about it was its cover. I know we shouldn’t &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2016/07/21/judging-books/&quot;&gt;judge books by their covers&lt;/a&gt; but I feel that as a designer, I’m even more susceptible to this. If I see a book with cool typography on its cover, I’ll check it out. That’s how this book got into my to-read list in the first place. I liked the cover, checked what it was about, found it interesting and added it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually don’t like to talk or write about politics. I find it very divisive. But every now and then, I do enjoy a book about it. This was one of them. I think my perception of this book was affected by The Rational Optimist which I had read just one month earlier. Rutger Bregman, the author, argues that despite the stupendous progress in the last two centuries (measured by life expectancy and per capita income) there hasn’t been a change in quality of life accompanying it. In fact, poverty is still a huge problem, so is our work-life balance. We work more to be able to afford less compared to the generations before ours. We were promised advent of robots would eliminate boring and repetitive jobs, reduce our weekly working hours and enable us to live fuller and happier lives. Instead, the opposite is true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rutger, also explores relatively radical ideas like giving free money to everyone, reduce our working hours to 15-a-week and introduce basic income. His case is compelling as he provides research backing these ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems we take the world around us for granted. Get up, commute to work, spend 8-10 hours in an uninspiring working environment, doing dull and boring work, only to spend another hour commuting back home, completely exhausted. I lived that life back in London and I did something about it. I think it’s time we start doing something about it collectively. Irrational exhaustion of human resources needs to stop and there are many ways to go about it (remote work which eliminates the need for commuting for example). But it seems we’re not ready yet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Discontent”, said Oscar Wilde, “is the first step in the progress of a man or a nation”.&lt;br /&gt;
—Rutger Bregman&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was discontent about my life when it was what everyone would regard as normal. &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely/&quot;&gt;Going back to working remotely&lt;/a&gt; improved it drastically for me. But that may not be an option for everyone. And as long as the masses of workers don’t feel discontent about it, our qualities of life won’t improve on the nation-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/34400335-utopia-for-realists&quot;&gt;Utopia for Realists on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;influence&quot;&gt;Influence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1391026083l/28815.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Robert B. Cialdini&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Robert B. Cialdini &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of the many books that I read about how our brains work in the decision-making process, Thinking Fast and Slow and How We Decide are two more. I read all three of them in 2018 but this one stood out the most. I think it must be the balance between the length of the content, the language used and the slick storytelling—something that the other two failed at. How We Decide was very well told and articulated through stories, while Thinking Fast and Slow was very condensed, with long chapters and sometimes seemingly unnecessary details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-1&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All three tell a similar story: we make decisions that are based on rationality or our emotions. We like to think that we’re in control of our decisions but we’re not. Completely different parts of our brains activate when taking different kind of decisions. The emotional part is the fast-thinking and the rational is the slower. But the tricky part is that we need both: emotional fast-thinking based on past experiences and urges keeps us alive in unexpected situations, the rational slow-thinking part allows us to solve complex problems. Influence is based on numerous psychological research and gives concrete, real-life examples of how to make better decisions and how certain entities (corporations) abuse this knowledge and trick us into buying the more expensive product or buy even what we don’t really need because &lt;em&gt;there are only x items left&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-1&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re not the rational beings we assume we are, and we’re easily tricked into doing things against our benefits on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28815.Influence&quot;&gt;Influence on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deep-work&quot;&gt;Deep work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1451409702l/28383248.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Cal Newport&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Cal Newport &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book was also on my to-read list for a while. I believe I added because someone recommended it but I never took the time to take a closer look and see what exactly it’s about. In April last year, I moved from London to Edinburgh and started working remotely for GitLab. I had worked remotely before but it was never a full-time position with a remote-only company. I didn’t know what exactly to expect but I knew I wanted to organise my working days better. Especially compared to my days back in London. I remembered of this book and decided to read it. I have been recommending it to all my remotely-working colleagues ever since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-2&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will depend on the type of person you are: you either like flexible working hours and work whenever you have time and “feel like it” or you need somewhat rigid frames to be productive. I’m the latter. If I don’t have structure, I waste time. I procrastinate, keep putting work off until it’s urgent. The worst thing is that in the end, I feel really bad about not being productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out there’s shallow work and then there’s deep work. Shallow work is when we’re busy working but keep switching between tasks, emails, Slack chat etc. We’re working, but we’re not productive. Deep work is the opposite. When we work deeply, we focus on one task, eliminate distractions and concentrate. Deep work is essential for any type of work creatives or technical people do (designers and developers). It’s really important to block out hours of time for deep work. Intervals of 2-3 hours work best. After reading this book, I reorganised my working days and also wrote &lt;a href=&quot;/articles/2018/05/17/remote-work-eliminate-distractions-getting-things-done/&quot;&gt;Eliminating distractions and getting things done&lt;/a&gt;  to document my process and help others do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-2&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blocking out time, reserved for focus is essential for deep work. And deep work is the most productive and effective way to solve complex problems or produce slick solutions. Take a look at how you spend your time. Track it for a couple of days if necessary. This will give you a great overview and you’ll be able to find room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28383248-deep-work&quot;&gt;Deep Work on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disrupted&quot;&gt;Disrupted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1471657959l/29744770.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Dan Lyons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Dan Lyons &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Funny thing. I don’t think I would ever read this book if it wasn’t on sale on Amazon for £0.95 and didn’t have a cool cover that attracted me immediately. I had no idea what to expect, I first thought it was a book about startups and how they disrupt markets with innovative products. It’s not. It’s about a journalist who loses his job as an editor of a popular magazine/website and joins a local startup. Reading this book felt like reading his journal about his experiences while working for this startup company—HubSpot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-3&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever worked for a startup with a “strong culture” and felt a bit weird or unfitting, you’ll identify with a lot of what Dan Lyons, the author, went through. He writes about typical startup bullshit: big promises that lead to disappointments, social pressures to fit in with “the culture” (or what I sometimes describe as “the cult”), the internal politics and about the coming to a realisation of what most of these startups are—money making machines  fuelled by hype. The more hype they manage to produce, the more millions the founders make. For most of these companies it’s not even about creating a useful product for the users, but more about “cashing in”. I went through similar experiences of trying to fit in with a “startup cult” and connected with the author on several points. &lt;em&gt;A hilarious and amusing read if you ever worked for a startup.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-3&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Startup jobs are exciting. The possibility of joining a small but growing company with great potential is very tempting. The problem is that most of these startups turn into something resembling cults. You either fit in or not. And this will be the biggest factor in how successful your time with that company will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29744770-disrupted&quot;&gt;Disrupted on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-daily-stoic&quot;&gt;The Daily stoic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1462161080l/29093292.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Ryan Holiday&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Ryan Holiday &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a book that I started reading in August 2017. It’s a book with 366 meditations and the reader is supposed to read one each day. Some go on and read more but I believe they miss the point of the book. The point is to adopt the stoic mentality one step at a time. It works really well if you establish a routine of reading the daily thought regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-4&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that each book I read changes me. It changes me the way I think as well as how I see the world and my role in it. Sometimes reading a book is merely about learning something new. I think that this book has changed me most profoundly from all the books that I read. It helped me understand the anger that I used to have about pretty much everything. By understanding it and where it came from, I was able to address it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the thoughts in the book are from the writings by Seneca—a Roman stoic philosopher—and Marcus Aurelius—the Roman emperor. The main point of stoicism is to not worry about things that are outside of your control and focus on the things that you &lt;strong&gt;can control&lt;/strong&gt;. This book has helped me make decisions that I would never be able to make without realising that. I keep reading the meditations every day even though I already read the whole book. I think I’ll keep reading them for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-take-away&quot;&gt;Key take away&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unhappiness in our lives is often triggered by the things outside of our control. This is especially true in our world driven by capitalism where we’re constantly pushed to be better than others, have more of everything and be perceived by everyone else as great and our lives as worthy of envy. If we’re content with what we have and not always yearn for more, we can actually achieve happiness. Unlike most things, our desires &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; under our control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Control your perceptions.&lt;br /&gt;
Direct your actions properly.&lt;br /&gt;
Willingly accept what’s outside your control.&lt;br /&gt;
That’s all we need to do.&lt;br /&gt;
—Ryan Holiday&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sounds simple, but it takes conscious effort every day to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29093292-the-daily-stoic&quot;&gt;The Daily Stoic on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it. These are my favourite 5 books of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/list/11006629-matej-latin?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;shelf=read&amp;amp;title=matej-latin&amp;amp;sort=date_read&amp;amp;order=d&quot;&gt;19 that I read this year&lt;/a&gt;. I hope that I gave you a few ideas on what to read next. What’s a cool book that you read this year? Can’t wait to see your recommendations in the comments below. :yum:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Books" /><category term="Psychology" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">Similarly to last year’s favourite books of 2017, I wanted to write a quick blog post about some of my favourite books that I read in 2018. Out of the 19 that I managed to read (exactly the same number as in 2017), here are my top 5. Keep in mind these are books I read in 2018, not necessarily released in 2018 and they’re not sorted in any particular order.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2 questions we ask designers in job interviews</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/10/25/2-questions-we-ask-designers-and-why/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2 questions we ask designers in job interviews" /><published>2018-10-25T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-25T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/10/25/2-questions-we-ask-designers-and-why</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/10/25/2-questions-we-ask-designers-and-why/">&lt;p&gt;We won’t ask you how many golf balls fit in a bus or how many times a day a clock’s hands overlap – nothing like what Google became famous for. While there’s some value in seeing how candidates react to curve-ball questions, they don’t really add much to a 45-minute interview. We also won’t ask you to attend an all-day session with a series of interviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/job-families/engineering/ux-designer/#hiring-process&quot;&gt;hiring process&lt;/a&gt; at GitLab is way simpler and more efficient. A successful candidate has to go through four stages of interviewing before receiving an offer. Altogether, we spend around 2-3 hours with them, so we need to ask the right questions to be efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so confident in the efficiency of these questions that I’m completely okay with sharing these publicly. &lt;em&gt;What&lt;/em&gt; you answer matters less than &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you answer them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the GitLab blog, &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/2018/10/25/two-questions-we-ask-ux-designers-in-job-interviews/&quot;&gt;read the full story here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Design" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">We won’t ask you how many golf balls fit in a bus or how many times a day a clock’s hands overlap – nothing like what Google became famous for. While there’s some value in seeing how candidates react to curve-ball questions, they don’t really add much to a 45-minute interview. We also won’t ask you to attend an all-day session with a series of interviewers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Buzz junkie</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Buzz junkie" /><published>2018-08-27T10:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-27T10:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/08/27/buzz-junkie/">&lt;p&gt;It’s early in the morning, probably around 7 because it’s still quite dark outside. I’m reading a book and trying to relax a bit before another busy day, my phone is resting on the table not too far away from me, but still out of reach. The book is about stoicism and a lot of topics in it are about having control over our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indent&quot;&gt;“Buzzz, buzzz!” The phone suddenly comes to life with vibrating sounds and light emitting from the screen that turns on. As it does, it slightly illuminates the dark room with its blueish glow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/smartphone.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photo by Andrew Guan&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by Andrew Guan &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wave of emotions hits me. Excitement, mixed with a bit of fear and anticipation—is it someone who needs my help? Someone from my subscribers telling me about their story? Is it someone sending me feedback about my book? I jump from my armchair and frantically rush to press the button to turn the screen back on. The moments seem like minutes before I finally get to see what the notifications is. It’s Twitter. “Rob White just liked a photo by Hung Lee…” What?! Who the fuck are these people and why the fuck should I care? You disturbed my morning routine, made me get up from the chair, destroyed my focus, made me feel anxious and interrupted me while reading the book and this is what I get in return?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What?! Who the fuck are these people and why the fuck should I&amp;nbsp;care?&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
I used to take my phone everywhere with me—always in my side pocket. I would jump on it like a starved lion jumps on a fresh piece of meat whenever it buzzed. I would check in on it even when it didn’t buzz. Shit, sometimes I would even check it a couple of times in a single minute. I always expected something important and meaningful to show up on that screen but most of the time, the screen was either full of junk or worse—empty. When it was empty I would go on and unlock the phone and start checking in on every app that I commonly used. &lt;em&gt;There’s gotta be something there but the notification probably didn’t come through&lt;/em&gt;, is what I was thinking.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been doing that for years and never saw anything wrong with it but then one day it hit me. I looked at myself from the third person. Jumping from whatever I was doing just to check the phone. Checking in even when it didn’t buzz. I was pathetic. Like a junkie, dependant on that dopamine rush but only to be let down every time. Like a mouse in an experiment not knowing what the sound brings, food or an electric shock. Like the people in casinos, putting the coins into the machine and pulling the lever always expecting that this time it will really be their time. This time they’ll hit the jackpot and become rich. But they never do. I wasn’t any better, I was a buzz junkie. Hooked to the meaninglessness of social media. How could I have been tricked into becoming such a fool? Why did I allow these corporations to come in and disrupt my personal life like that? Why did I allow to feel nervous and agitated all the time because of this shit? It brings no value to me. Absolutely zero. So why keep doing it? At that moment, I found it ironic that I had been reading a book about stoicism and having control over my life for almost a year but only realised that so late. I had very little control over my life and I needed to do something about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;breaking-a-habit&quot;&gt;Breaking a habit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did, I disabled all notifications except messages. I never had the Facebook app on my phone and now it was time to delete a few more. I always used the ‘Do not disturb’ mode that comes with iOS and set it from 10 pm to 7 am. I go to sleep at 10 in the evening and get up at 6 in the morning so that meant I only had one hour of distraction-free time. That’s crazy, why would I allow meaningless shit to agitate me right before I go to sleep? Why would I want to start my day with this meaningless shit? I changed the ‘Do not disturb’ mode to start at 8 pm and end at 9 am. Now nobody can disturb and agitate me two hours before I go to sleep and 3 hours after I wake up. This had a tremendous effect on not feeling anxious all the time. I feel more relaxed in general, I don’t look for meaningless distractions, I can focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I feel more relaxed in general, I don’t look for meaningless distractions, I can focus.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
It took some time to get used to these changes. Occasionally, I still felt the urge to check on my phone and I had to make a conscious decision to stop myself from doing it. It &lt;em&gt;needs to be a&lt;/em&gt; conscious decision until we get used to it, it’s the only way to rewire our brain. I still get that urge sometimes when I glance at my phone lying somewhere, just waiting for me to turn the screen on and see what cool things it has in store for me. Most times I manage to resist the urge, sometimes I give in. It takes a long time to break a habit. But breaking a bad habit is liberating and worth the effort. I don’t feel as anxious and constantly agitated anymore. I feel I finally have peace of mind.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to feel sorry for people that are hooked on drugs… but aren’t we all hooked on something? It can be as innocent as sugar and coffee or something more destructive—cigarettes, social media… How do you use your phone? What is your relationship with social media like? &lt;a href=&quot;#comments&quot;&gt;Comment bellow&lt;/a&gt; because I’d love to hear your stories.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">It’s early in the morning, probably around 7 because it’s still quite dark outside. I’m reading a book and trying to relax a bit before another busy day, my phone is resting on the table not too far away from me, but still out of reach. The book is about stoicism and a lot of topics in it are about having control over our lives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Standups suck, and here’s how to fix them</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/06/03/standups-suck/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Standups suck, and here’s how to fix them" /><published>2018-06-03T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-03T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/06/03/standups-suck</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/06/03/standups-suck/">&lt;div&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    This is how my usual mornings went.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d get to the office at around 8:30 am—a bit early so I had some time to sort out my desk and check email. My first standup was at 9:20 am. This was the design standup which should have taken about 10 minutes but quite often extended to double its allocated time. I then had 20 minutes till the next standup at 10 am. This was the one that always started late and usually extended well over the allocated time. Right after that one, at 10:15 am was the next standup. This one usually took about 15 minutes to get through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for Mind the Product and you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mindtheproduct.com/2018/05/standups-suck-and-heres-how-to-fix-them/&quot;&gt;read the full story here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">This is how my usual mornings went.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Going back to working remotely</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Going back to working remotely" /><published>2018-05-24T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-24T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/05/24/going-back-to-working-remotely/">&lt;p&gt;It’s a regular working day but I’m not sitting in an office, rushing from one meeting to another. Not anymore and it’s because I decided to go back to working remotely. I spent the last five years getting up really early, commuting to work, attending standups, hurrying to meetings and hoping that I would be able to get some work done before time runs out. It’s a never ending struggle. No matter how optimistic you are, the number of meetings never really reduces. Commuting to an office, even if it’s just a 20-minute walk, can never be pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we lived in Greenwich, which is one of the nicest areas in London, I had to get up at 5 in the morning. I’m one of those that like to have a strong morning routine. Before I would always get up at 6 just so that I had one hour that I could spend either reading or exercising (it’s something that helps me remain sane no matter how much stress there is in my life). But this was the first time that I had to commute to an office in central London and it took around one hour.  I didn’t want to let go of my routine so it had to be moved because of that. Do I have to tell you that I never really managed to stick to it? 5 in the morning was simply to early. I only had 7 hours of sleep (on good nights) and it simply wasn’t enough. In the end, living in a nice area meant nothing because I never had time or energy to explore and enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-cog-in-a-machine&quot;&gt;A cog in a machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commuting, not enough sleep, not being productive at work… all these things meant that I had very little control over my life. By the time I got home I was completely spent, I had no energy to work on my personal projects. You don’t realise it at first but after a while, it hits you—you’re nothing but a cog in a machine. You show up, react to “emergencies”, but don’t stand out. If the cog doesn’t align well, the machine breaks down. And that’s exactly how it’s supposed to work—a cog’s job is not being extra productive, it’s fitting in and keep running things as they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;What the hell are all these people doing? Sitting there, wasting their lives away…&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
  I remember looking through the tall glass windows from the office that I used to work at. On one side, a gorgeous view of central London, dozens of similar glass buildings on the other. They were so close to ours that I could clearly see people sitting in rows of tables. I couldn’t help but think: “&lt;em&gt;what the hell are all these people doing? Sitting there, wasting their lives away….  Wait! Do they look at me and think the same thing? I’m sitting there, 8 hours every day with 100 other people distributed among the rows of desks.&lt;/em&gt;” We’re all like chickens—sitting in rows and laying eggs until one day when we stop being useful because our eggs aren’t good enough anymore. We all know what happens then.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five years into it and I had enough. How the hell do people manage to do this for their whole lives? Fuck that, I don’t want to grow old and look back at all the things that could be but never were. All the years spent working my ass of but nothing to show for it. Something had to change and as it seems now, the solution was surprisingly simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-working-remotely-help&quot;&gt;How does working remotely help?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had worked remotely before when I freelanced but it was never full-time. And it was never for a fully-remote company. The only difference in my routine is that now I actually manage to stick with it. I still get up early, exercise, read, get to work at the same time, have lunch at the same time and wrap up work at roughly the same time as well. Without commuting, I now have more energy to spend on actually working. In general, I have more time to spend with my family (my wife and our cat for now) and I also have enough energy to spend working on my own things in the evening—without burning out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;No standups, few meetings and no need for my working hours to overlap with the colleagues from across the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;force-indent&quot;&gt;
  Working for a company like GitLab also helps a lot. Because we work on a tool that helps people collaborate asynchronously, we’re encouraged to work asynchronously ourselves. That means no standups, only few meetings and unlike most remote companies, no need for my working hours to overlap with the colleagues from across the ocean. The other day I washed my car in the morning and it wasn’t a problem even though it took me a couple of hours (believe it or not, I really enjoy washing my car 😅). I’m now in the coffee shop writing this post and I’ll go home shortly after and spend a few hours working and actually being productive.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this is something I had before but I never really appreciated it until I experienced the other side. I started this journey through Europe five years ago, looking for a collaborative and engaging office environment but found the exact opposite. I had to go through that to realise that what I was looking for was something that I already had in the first place. A brick and mortar office doesn’t necessarily mean that you’ll be in good company or productive. And it certainly doesn’t make work more enjoyable (in most cases it’s the opposite).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working remotely comes with its own set of challenges but can also give you a better control over your life. That’s something that really matters to me and that’s what ultimately lead me to make a decision to go back to working like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is your work life? Do you work in an office or remotely? How is it working out for you? Share your thoughts with me in the &lt;a href=&quot;#comments&quot;&gt;comments bellow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">It’s a regular working day but I’m not sitting in an office, rushing from one meeting to another. Not anymore and it’s because I decided to go back to working remotely. I spent the last five years getting up really early, commuting to work, attending standups, hurrying to meetings and hoping that I would be able to get some work done before time runs out. It’s a never ending struggle. No matter how optimistic you are, the number of meetings never really reduces. Commuting to an office, even if it’s just a 20-minute walk, can never be pleasant.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Eliminating distractions and getting things done</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/05/17/remote-work-eliminate-distractions-getting-things-done/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Eliminating distractions and getting things done" /><published>2018-05-17T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-17T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/05/17/remote-work-eliminate-distractions-getting-things-done</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/articles/2018/05/17/remote-work-eliminate-distractions-getting-things-done/">&lt;p&gt;I lived in London for the past three years and worked for two companies in this time: a late-stage startup and an enterprise. Both are trying to emulate the early-stage startup working environment by designing an open-plan office. It sounds great, but if it’s not done right, it isn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this article for the GitLab blog, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://about.gitlab.com/2018/05/17/eliminating-distractions-and-getting-things-done/&quot;&gt;read it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Remote" /><summary type="html">I lived in London for the past three years and worked for two companies in this time: a late-stage startup and an enterprise. Both are trying to emulate the early-stage startup working environment by designing an open-plan office. It sounds great, but if it’s not done right, it isn’t.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">If you lived here…</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/03/30/if-you-lived-here/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="If you lived here…" /><published>2018-03-30T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/03/30/if-you-lived-here</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/03/30/if-you-lived-here/">&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/if-you-lived-here.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;If you lived here…&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;If you lived here… (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.e-flux.com/journal/09/61370/under-privileged-spaces-on-martha-rosler-s-if-you-lived-here-8230/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheap, red bricks, tiny windows, wooden-fenced square gardens, every house is exactly the same as the one next to it. Wet soil from the morning rain as there’s no grass anywhere, it’s desolated with no signs of life at all. Just the grey clouds in the sky and the cold wind howling around the box-shaped houses. “Bleak” is the perfect word to describe it. I have no idea how much it costs but it must be a couple of hundreds of thousands at least. I can’t help but see it as a sad place where dreams come to die. A place full of emotionally frustrated people whose best chance to live a dream is to live a broken dream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a park in the middle of the town, clearly meant for children to play but nobody’s there. It looks like nobody ever was there at all. The few people that do live there are probably too busy commuting to London and their important jobs. Why even bother putting a park in it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m on my way to Manchester but thousands of people ride this train the opposite way to spend 8–10 hours in London and come home exhausted and emotionally spent. I know how it feels because I was there. I used to spend one hour commuting each way. And the trains are not what you imagine they are. They don’t even feel like a train, they feel like being stuck in a can of fish. They’re crowded to the point where you’re standing with your bag in your hand and can’t even move your arms because there’s literally no room. The bag that only weights a couple of kilos becoming heavier with each second that passes by, sweat pouring down your forehead, all the way to the eyes but you can’t swipe it. You can’t move, you’re stuck. And just when you thought it couldn’t get worse, the train stops at London Bridge — one of the busiest train stations in London. The train is completely full but there’s two times more people outside trying to board it. I get pushed further into the middle of the coach and I start fearing if I’ll be able to get off when the train reaches my station. Every breath gets heavier as the smell inside the train intensifies. I feel someone breathing down my neck, I hear another person’s music even though I’m listening to my own. I thought at first it couldn’t get worse but it did. But it will get even worse as the train keeps stopping and more people push their way onboard. Young mothers with baby strollers, commuters with bicycles… where are all these people coming from?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you lived here you’d be almost home? No thanks. I’m leaving London behind. It was a dream that turned out to be another broken dream. But broken dreams are there to teach us that what we want isn’t necessarily what we really need. And through that, we grow, we evolve and we mature. I’m thankful I tried living the London dream and I’m glad it turned out to be broken. Now I get to move to the next one. I refuse to live a life of frustrations, distractions and wasted time. A life of unexplored “what ifs”. A life that is outside of my control.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">If you lived here… (Source)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I never studied design</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/02/17/i-never-studied-design/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I never studied design" /><published>2018-02-17T09:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-17T09:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/02/17/i-never-studied-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2018/02/17/i-never-studied-design/">&lt;p&gt;I come from a small, seaside town in Slovenia. By the time I finished high school I had already been designing and building websites for a couple of years. There was no digital design course in any of the faculties in Slovenia at the time so I decided to sign up for the Computer Science course in Ljubljana—Slovenia’s capital. I didn’t know what to expect but shortly after I started the course I realized that it wasn’t for me. Looking back now, I think I just wasn’t mature enough to see the potential in learning Java and stuff. So I dropped out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dropping out meant that I had to move back to my hometown and sign up for a course there. With a limited range of those available locally, I decided to study Management. Not because I had a dream of becoming a manager or an economist, it was simply the most generic option out there. And you know what they say—you need a degree to even stand a chance to get a job. All this time I was still designing and building stuff. Not just websites, but user interfaces and user experiences as well. I started out being completely clueless what UX design actually is. Whenever I didn’t know something, I improvised, made mistakes and learned from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there was no course guiding me towards “what I should be learning” I basically learned a bit of everything. I was frustrated by doing everything for my clients until I learned about the T-shaped skills at some point. I then decided to become a &lt;a href=&quot;https://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2017/08/06/specialised-generalist/&quot;&gt;specialised generalist&lt;/a&gt; and systematically develop my skills which included front-end development, writing, management, UX research so they would complement my UX/UI and visual design skills well. I was never happy doing just one step in the process and handing it over to the next person in line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had a privilege of not being able to study design.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about it now, I believe I had a privilege of not being able to study design. Privilege because I had to learn everything I know by myself. It’s a privilege also because I had the passion for doing design driving me onward. So I actually ended up doing what I really love, it was never just a fling. It was, and still is a journey driven by excitement of creating things and a hunger for learning. It started out as a dream, a hobby even. I never planned on becoming a designer but at some point it became a dream. A dream that was up to me to fulfil. And in the end, it was a privilege because I didn’t follow an established path towards becoming a designer. I learned what I had to, to get the job done, not something that a professor threw into a course’s curriculum. It was never something I could take for granted, it was something I had to fight for. If I wanted to be a designer, I simply had to do what designers do. That’s it, it’s as simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Design" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><summary type="html">I come from a small, seaside town in Slovenia. By the time I finished high school I had already been designing and building websites for a couple of years. There was no digital design course in any of the faculties in Slovenia at the time so I decided to sign up for the Computer Science course in Ljubljana—Slovenia’s capital. I didn’t know what to expect but shortly after I started the course I realized that it wasn’t for me. Looking back now, I think I just wasn’t mature enough to see the potential in learning Java and stuff. So I dropped out.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My favourite books of 2017</title><link href="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My favourite books of 2017" /><published>2017-12-22T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-22T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://matejlatin.co.uk/personal-notes/2017/12/22/my-favourite-books-of-2017/">&lt;p&gt;Last year I challenged myself to read 40 books, this year, I skipped that challenge. Reading has become such an integral part of my life that I don’t need to trick myself into doing it anymore (challenging myself to read that many books was a way to build a strong routine). Before that, I had to force myself to start reading a new book. Now, I can’t wait to dig into the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here’s a list of books that I read this year and really liked. They’re not sorted in any particular order and none of them is directly design-related. I would categorise most of them as books about productivity, entrepreneurship, business and life in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-100-startup&quot;&gt;The $100 Startup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1388254436l/18883826.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Chris Guillebeau&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Chris Guillebeau &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first book that I read immediately after the new year. I received a Kindle Paperwhite as a Christmas gift and this was the first book that I bought with it. I loved the book so much, that I read it in just a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris Guillebeau (the author) is a guy in his early thirties and never had a “real job”. He wrote the book as he travelled around the world on his quest to visit every country. I believe that by the time he wrote the book, he managed to visit 175 nations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris is an inspiration. He manages to live a lifestyle he wants and be completely free. He tells stories of other ordinary people that managed to break free. Free of “real jobs”, free of office desks an cubicles, free of all the bullshit. It was this book that inspired me to finally make one of my ideas happen—Better Web Type. You don’t need a lot of money to start your business. You just need to get shit done. And if what you’re selling is helpful to people, they will buy. And you can prove that what you’re saying is valuable by giving away stuff for free. We’ll get back to this concept later in the post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway&quot;&gt;Key takeaway:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That idea that has been on your mind for the past few years? Go on and do it. “What if it fails?” is probably lurking somewhere in your mind. But what if it doesn’t? There’s nothing to lose.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18883826-the-100-startup&quot;&gt;$100 Startup on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;good-togreat&quot;&gt;Good to Great&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1435813395l/76865.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Jim Collins&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Jim Collins &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Good is the enemy of great”—is the first sentence in this book. What a great start. I got this book for a couple of pounds on Amazon (used copy). It was a great investment in my understanding of business organisations and what makes the best ones stand out. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-1&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jim Collins and his team of researchers spent 5 years researching American companies that stood out in their fields. After 6,000 articles and 2,000 pages of interviews transcript they came up with a list of a dozen of truly great companies. But the really important part was that they had a theory about what made these companies great and wrote down 7 key contributing factors and explored them. Definitely recommend this one but I have to warn you: reading it, you might realise that you work for a shit company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-1&quot;&gt;Key takeaway:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any company can become a great company but most don’t know how but even if they do, they’re afraid to face the inevitable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/76865.Good_to_Great&quot;&gt;Good to great on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-startup-ownersmanual&quot;&gt;The Startup Owner’s Manual&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1448890528l/13557008.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Steve Blank&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Steve Blank &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been wanting to read this one for a while but kinda dreaded it because it’s a huge, 600+ pages book. I worked for an early-stage startup at the time I added this book to my to-read list but I’m glad I kept putting it off. A few years later it helped me improve my process of validating what to do next with my personal projects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-2&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the book that needs to be on your desk if you work in product design &amp;amp; development. Especially if you’re in a small team or maybe even by yourself. It will help you find out if there’s a market for the thing that you’re building. The process is basically split into two steps: customer discovery and customer validation. What I really liked about the edition of the book that I read was that it had sections dedicated to building digital products. I walked away with a much better understanding of how to approach building a product (or even a company), and many ideas I could put to test straight away. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-2&quot;&gt;Key takeaway:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can find answers to pretty much anything by experimenting early and often.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13557008-the-startup-owner-s-manual&quot;&gt;The Startup Owner’s Manual on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-afuck&quot;&gt;The Subtle Art of Not Giving a Fuck&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1480903131l/29965800.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Mark Manson&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Mark Manson &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read this book because I got it for £1 through a Kindle promotion and because I liked the cover (yes, I judge books by their covers). I wasn’t expecting much from it but was pleasantly surprised. I was afraid it would fall into the category of self-help books which I generally dislike. Instead, it was a story that I could closely relate to. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-3&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For decades, we’ve been told that positive thinking is the key to a happy, rich life. “Fuck positivity,” Mark Manson says. There’s a lot of shit in the world and the more fucks we give about everything, the more miserable we’ll be. Mark’s point is: there only so many things we can give a fuck about and we need to choose wisely what those things will be. Are your colleagues (schoolmates, whatever…) a bunch of morons who keep finding ways to pick on you? Fuck them. Are your parents selfish idiots to the point where they managed to ruin your childhood? Fuck them. Is the mainstream media trying to persuade you into believing that you’re in constant danger and the only thing that can help is buying (even) more stuff? Fuck them. Is your partner abusive, has a sense of entitlement of controlling your life and doesn’t let you live as you want? Fuck him too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark draws inspiration from minimalism, stoicism (which is something I’ve been reading about a lot lately) and his personal life stories. By the end, I really felt like I knew him personally. A very interesting, inspiring read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-3&quot;&gt;Key takeaway:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You need to choose what’s important in your life and eliminate everything else. It’s hard to bring down a man who doesn’t give a flying fuck.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/29965800-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-f-ck&quot;&gt;The Subtle Art of Not Giving a Fuck on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-curve&quot;&gt;The Curve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure class=&quot;image floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://images.gr-assets.com/books/1408925341l/19018255.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;By Nicholas Lovell&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;By Nicholas Lovell &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I literally stumbled upon this book while browsing on my Kindle. Amazon suggested this book to me and their suggestion was spot on. Better Web Type had been released for a couple of months already when I read this book. Reading it, I realised that I built exactly what was described in it—unawarely of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-so-good-about-it-4&quot;&gt;What’s so good about it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nicholas Lovell wrote this book based on his experience from building F2P (free-to-play) video games. But he manages to expand the book into other areas and does it well. His premises: build valuable things and give them away for free. Build a relationship with your customers based on trust and they’ll be ready to spend a lot of money on things that matter to them. The concept is simple: get in a lot of users by giving away stuff for free. Most of them will never buy from you, the majority of those that will buy, will spend an average amount on things you sell. But there will be a small amount of diehard fans that will be willing to spend lots of cash on things that really matter to them—that’s where the name—“The Curve”—comes from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;key-takeaway-4&quot;&gt;Key takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Build your customer relationship on trust and you’ll never have trouble selling your product.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19018255-the-curve&quot;&gt;The Curve on Goodreads →&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. These are my favourite 5 books of the 19 that I read this year. I hope that I gave you a few ideas on what to read next. What’s a cool book that you read this year? Can’t wait to see your recommendations in the comments below. :yum:&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Books" /><summary type="html">Last year I challenged myself to read 40 books, this year, I skipped that challenge. Reading has become such an integral part of my life that I don’t need to trick myself into doing it anymore (challenging myself to read that many books was a way to build a strong routine). Before that, I had to force myself to start reading a new book. Now, I can’t wait to dig into the next one.</summary></entry></feed>