<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-11-25T20:48:34+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Matej Latin</title><subtitle>Matej Latin is a UX/UI designer working for Auto Trader UK in London. He writes about design, minimalism and typography.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What it’s all about</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/11/25/what-its-all-about/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What it’s all about" /><published>2017-11-25T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2017-11-25T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/11/25/what-its-all-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/11/25/what-its-all-about/">&lt;p&gt;I created the course because I felt there was no concise way to learn the skills required to make typography an integral part of a web design process. The gap between designers and developers is still there and I haven’t seen many projects that are trying to address that. Better Web Type at its core is exactly that—it starts off explaining typography, how it works, why web developers need to learn about it and then shows them how. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Because I never expected it to grow as much as it did, I also didn’t expect there would eventually be costs to cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never really expected to make money from the project and I also never expected that it would grow as it did. So far, it has helped more than 15,000 designers and developers understand web typography and—what’s more important—enabled them to work together better. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago, one of the biggest fans and supporters of my work—Harry—sent me an email after he purchased my book for the second time, this time in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com/web-typography-book&quot;&gt;newly released paperback format&lt;/a&gt; (Harry if you’re reading, cheers!). He told me how much my work has helped him improve his and sent me a design he was working on. He got everything right: the contrast, the whitespace, the typefaces, the scale, the horizontal rhythm, the vertical rhythm, the punctuation… everything! It was a textbook execution of all the stuff I wrote about in the Better Web Type book. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two magic moments that happen in the process of starting your own business:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when you sell your product for the first time and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;when you realise how helpful it is to the people who buy it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The example I described above was clearly the second of the two. But unlike the first one, the second one can be a repeating event. I keep getting positive emails from people I helped so far. Sometimes people even send me physical mail like postcards, which I find pretty cool. :stuck_out_tongue_closed_eyes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s my secret:&lt;/strong&gt; yes, it’s really cool when someone buys the book and I earn a couple of dollars because of that. It helps me cover the costs of running this project plus a little something extra on top—something I can put in my savings. I still get excited every time someone buys the book, just like the first time it happened. But I get even more excited when I receive an email like the one mentioned above. It makes me happy to a point where it brings a tear to my eye. And with every such email I receive, with contrast to the book sale moment, this feeling gets amplified. I feel better about my work when I see how helpful it is to other people. And this is what it’s all about. It’s not the what or how, it’s the why. And my why is simple—help designers and developers understand typography and help them work together better. That’s it. It really is as simple as that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t seen it yet, make sure you take a look at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=u4ZoJKF_VuA&amp;amp;t=6s&quot;&gt;Start With Why&lt;/a&gt; by Simon Sinek.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Startup" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">I created the course because I felt there was no concise way to learn the skills required to make typography an integral part of a web design process. The gap between designers and developers is still there and I haven’t seen many projects that are trying to address that. Better Web Type at its core is exactly that—it starts off explaining typography, how it works, why web developers need to learn about it and then shows them how. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The day I proved myself wrong</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/08/25/the-day-i-proved-myself-wrong/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The day I proved myself wrong" /><published>2017-08-25T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-25T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/08/25/the-day-i-proved-myself-wrong</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/08/25/the-day-i-proved-myself-wrong/">&lt;p&gt;Designers don’t know why a small change to an interface results in a massive drop in a core business metric, product managers don’t know what should go into the backlog and what not, developers don’t know how to estimate the delivery time of the fancy new feature. The whole team behind the product is so clueless that they don’t even know if the new feature brings any value to the users. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We come up with our pity assumptions and hypothesis and we try to validate them. We try to show that we’re right, that’s what we’re being paid for right? Being smart and all… We’re certain we’re right… until we’re proven wrong. Time and time again. But even then, we doubt the validity of the test and we doubt the meaning of a metric if we need to. So we run another A/B test or more user testing sessions. We spend days or even weeks to get a similar result. Another result that we don’t really know how to interpret. The process feels like making tiny steps in the dark—expecting meaningful results by doing the same thing over and over again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Certainty is the enemy of growth. Nothing is for certain until it has already happened—and even then, it’s debatable. That’s why accepting the inevitable imperfections of our values is necessary for any growth to take place. Instead of striving for certainty, we should be in constant search of doubt… Instead of looking to be right all the time, we should be looking for how we’re wrong all the time. Because we are. Being wrong opens up to the possibility of change.&lt;br /&gt;
—Mark Manson&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our industry is plagued with certainty. Smartass people with thick heads who are certain in their own work because they have been doing it for 10+ years or whatever. I came across many people like that but in a way, we’re all the same. It’s our process of creating something and then proving that it’s correct that is wrong. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-real-life-example&quot;&gt;A real-life example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long ago, we had a discussion at work. If you go to a typical car ad on Auto Trader today, you’ll see that it’s being sold by a “Trade Seller”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wrong-01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain group of people inside the company believe that it should be replaced with the actual name of the company selling the car because it would be clearer to the user. I am one of those people. We even had discussions of including that seller information (including their rating) in the search results. So I decided to prove that the “Trade Seller” bit is confusing the users. I was certain that they don’t understand what it means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wrong-02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I devised two tests with Usability Hub in a way that the results could be easily quantified. I mocked up search results with seller rating in two versions: one with “Trade Seller + rating” and another one with “Actual seller name + rating”. I was looking to answer two questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do users understand what the “Trade seller / actual seller name mean”?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And  do they understand what is the rating next to it referring to? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in reality, I was certain to prove:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that people don’t understand what “Trade seller” means and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that they won’t understand that the rating is of the seller when placed next to the “Trade seller” text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wrong-03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results were surprising and humbling. I did find answers to both questions but they were the complete opposite of what I wanted to prove. The results showed that people do understand what “Trade seller” means. Actually, in the test most of them knew exactly what it meant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wrong-04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s where it gets crazy. Not only did the participants understand what “Trade seller” means. They understood what the rating is of better when it was next to “Trade seller” instead of the actual name of the seller. In the v1 of the test (“Trade seller”), 86% of participants knew what it meant and 93% of them said that the rating is of the seller. In the v2, 100% of participants claimed that the names were the car dealerships that were selling the listed cars but only 46% of them said that the rating is of the seller. The rest assumed it was a rating of the car.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wrong-05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I proved myself wrong on both accounts. People know what “Trade seller” means and they understand that the rating next to it is of the seller and not of the car (I ran the test two times with a total of 40 participants for each version, just to be sure).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The A/B test was already planned and ready to go. I had to stop it, so we could first see if users understand the information correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we only found out about that because of the way the test was devised—qualitative feedback that can be quantified. The initial plan was to simply run a quantitative A/B test and see if it has an effect on our core business metrics. That would never teach us what we learned through this simple test. We couldn’t interpret the result correctly because we wouldn’t know if the users even understand the information presented. But the worst part is: we wouldn’t even know that. We would end up with an uneducated guess and we wouldn’t even realise it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always leave room for uncertainty. Not to the point where we’re paralysed by it and scared to make a choice. Decide based on the information you have at the moment but question your solution. Assume it’s wrong and try to prove it’s wrong. Failing is a better way to learn than running A/B tests to (sometimes falsely) confirm the validity of your solution. Forget your ego and forget your entitlement to be correct. Even if you have been doing this for years. Or maybe especially because of that. Things change, we need to remain humble and admit that we don’t understand everything and that we make mistakes. But if we admit it, we can learn from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Subtle Art of Not Giving a Fuck&lt;/em&gt; by Mark Manson (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/28257707-the-subtle-art-of-not-giving-a-f-ck?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">Designers don’t know why a small change to an interface results in a massive drop in a core business metric, product managers don’t know what should go into the backlog and what not, developers don’t know how to estimate the delivery time of the fancy new feature. The whole team behind the product is so clueless that they don’t even know if the new feature brings any value to the users. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Specialised generalist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/08/06/specialised-generalist/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Specialised generalist" /><published>2017-08-06T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-06T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/08/06/specialised-generalist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/08/06/specialised-generalist/">&lt;p&gt;Compared to them, I felt mediocre and I was frustrated because of it. You see, I never specialised in anything. Since I was a child, I had a habit of putting things together and create something out of that. I saw things differently from others. Where everyone else saw a cardboard box, I saw a cool military jeep that I could create out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was different. Or at least, at that point I thought it was. I was studying management and economics at a local university when I turned my hobby into a small business that was enough to get by. I was doing proper UX/UI design work for clients worldwide. Looking back, I now realise I was doing well. But that didn’t mean much to me. People wouldn’t hire me to draw pretty illustrations and they wouldn’t hire me to do front-end development stuff. They hired me to bring their brands to life (yes back then I did that sort of work too) and design their websites. They hired me to design user experiences and do pretty much everything design-related for them—including building and deploying the websites I designed for their projects.  Believe it or not, that only fueled my frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skills-before.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These would be the skills that I had then. Enough of each to get by, but not really specialised in anything. At least that’s how I felt at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;t-shaped-skills&quot;&gt;T-shaped skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, one day, I stumbled upon the “T-shaped skills” concept. I had never heard of anything similar before. Let’s take a look at what exactly it means: &lt;em&gt;Having skills and knowledge that are both deep and broad&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I decided to dig deeper and I learned that generalists (people with such skills) are in high demand at some of the best companies. Companies that solve tough problems using the so-called design thinking. That was the first time that I saw my lack of specialism as something that could potentially be good. Looking back now, it seems that at that moment, I made a subconscious decision to become a generalist. A while later it became clear to me that being a generalist is an amazing thing (and that I was a generalist already anyway) so I made a conscious decision to specialise in that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/t-shaped-skills.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, generalists don’t necessarily have average skills all around. The name “generalist” tends to imply that but it’s not true. Once I decided to become a proper generalist I decided that UX/UI would be my main skill so I would put most effort into improving that. But being a generalist means that I put a lot of effort into picking up other, complementing skills. Web design, native apps design, visual design, front-end development, design-thinking, prototyping etc. They would all get an equally important part in acquiring and developing skills. And it’s not just acquiring skills for the sake of it. It’s acquiring skills with an intent to use them or in most cases even acquiring skills by using them before acquiring them (learning by doing)—which often requires improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/skills-now.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal changed from naively striving to be the best at everything (and wasting energy and time to get there) to making small and systematic steps towards becoming the &lt;em&gt;most complete designer I can be&lt;/em&gt;. Since I consciously started working on specialising as a generalist, my skills set is more complete. I know that my illustration and animation skills are still quite basic, but so far, they were always good enough. That’s what being a generalist means to me: knowing how to apply the skills you already have and pick up new ones when needed and apply them immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-is-being-a-generalist-a-goodthing&quot;&gt;Why is being a generalist a good thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;People possessing these [broad] skills are able to shape their knowledge to fit the problem at hand rather than insist that their problems appear in a particular, recognizable form. Given their wide experience in applying functional knowledge, they are capable of convergent, synergistic thinking&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s think about a real-life scenario. We have two teams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team A:&lt;/em&gt; Sam is a UX/UI designer with an interest in front-end development and product design/management. Other members of the team are John, a full-stack web developer and Scarlet, a product manager. John has a particular interest in UX and design in general. Scarlet, the product manager, has some UX background and loves doing UX research and customer development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Team B:&lt;/em&gt; Allison is a UI designer. She likes to create pretty things and hates when other people make her push pixels around. Emma is a UX designer, she loves creating wireframes and prototypes. She’s comfortable with letting Allison take over from there. Peter is a product manager, he loves coming up with ideas for products and thinks that’s his responsibility. Eric is a full-stack developer as he does both: back- and front-end development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The need for T-shaped skills surfaces anywhere problem solving is required across different deep functional knowledge bases or at the juncture of such deep knowledge with an application area.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Leonard-Barton&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research suggests, that people who have broad skills communicate and work with others better. It makes sense: because Sam from team A knows a bit about front-end development, it’s much easier to talk to web developers and explain what needs to be done. The same goes the other way, John—team A’s full-stack developer knows a bit about design so he can suggest improvements the designer might have missed. Team A is a small squad that has the skills and the mentality required to find out what needs to be built and then go on and build it. Put a good product development process on top of that and the chances of success rise dramatically. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Team B on the other hand, is much more likely to have communication issues. Designers that aren’t comfortable getting feedback early and often can’t function in teams that need to move fast. Product managers that think that coming up with product ideas is solely their responsibility are hard to work with because they hate it when people question their ideas. Allison, the UX designer likes the wireframing and prototyping part but doesn’t have a habit of seeing products through to the end. Eric, the team B’s full-stack developer is the person that comes closest to being a generalist. But it’s not enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying that everyone should aim to become a generalist. There’s room for specialists in product development teams too. But there needs to be the right balance of the two. What I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; saying though is that being a generalist is fun. Having a holistic overview of the product development process and see things through to the end. Making sure that things get built as they were intended and learn how to improve with the next iteration at the same time. I don’t really think it’s just about acquiring and using different skills—It’s a mentality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The meaning of “T-shaped” skills (&lt;a href=&quot;http://wordspy.com/index.php?word=t-shaped&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;T-shaped professionals, T-shaped skills, hybrid managers (&lt;a href=&quot;http://coevolving.com/blogs/index.php/archive/t-shaped-professionals-t-shaped-skills-hybrid-managers/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">Compared to them, I felt mediocre and I was frustrated because of it. You see, I never specialised in anything. Since I was a child, I had a habit of putting things together and create something out of that. I saw things differently from others. Where everyone else saw a cardboard box, I saw a cool military jeep that I could create out of it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Better web typography for a better web</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/books/2017/07/31/better-web-typography-for-a-better-web/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Better web typography for a better web" /><published>2017-07-31T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2017-07-31T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/books/2017/07/31/better-web-typography-for-a-better-web</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/books/2017/07/31/better-web-typography-for-a-better-web/">&lt;figure class=&quot;full-bleed-image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/better-web-type-book.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I launched an email course called Better Web Type on 14 February this year. It introduces the topic of typography to people who actually design and build websites—web designers and web developers. Split into 10 daily lessons, it covers topics like rhythm in web typography, how to use modular scales, how to combine typefaces and similar. It was featured in &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/equilateral-triangle-perfect-paragraph/&quot;&gt;CSS-tricks&lt;/a&gt;, as a cover feature in the Net magazine, in the Web Designer magazine, as well as sites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://tympanus.net/codrops/collective/collective-295/&quot;&gt;Codrops&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2017/06/web-development-reading-list-186/&quot;&gt;Smashing Magazine&lt;/a&gt;. The course is highly-rated with an average of 4.7 out of 5 after more than 700 reviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students that went through the course loved it so much that they started asking for a book. Writing a book on the same topic was always on my roadmap but the high demand turned it into my top priority. The book was released as an eBook on July 31 and is available to &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com/web-typography-book&quot;&gt;order on the Better Web Type website&lt;/a&gt;. A paperback version will follow shortly.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="books" /><category term="Typography" /><category term="Web-design" /><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bwt-cover" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Equilateral triangle of a perfect paragraph</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/articles/2017/06/09/equilateral-triangle-of-a-perfect-paragraph/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Equilateral triangle of a perfect paragraph" /><published>2017-06-09T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2017-06-09T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/articles/2017/06/09/equilateral-triangle-of-a-perfect-paragraph</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/articles/2017/06/09/equilateral-triangle-of-a-perfect-paragraph/">&lt;p&gt;And the lack of knowledge about typography doesn’t come from ignorance. I learned that web designers are commonly either self-taught and haven’t grasped the importance of typography yet, or they actually studied design but typography was just one of the classes they had to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com&quot;&gt;Better Web Type&lt;/a&gt; course to help raise awareness of the important role typography plays on the web. In my opinion, both web designers and web developers should learn the basics—if a designer uses ligatures in her designs but the developer doesn’t even know what ligatures are, how can we expect him to correctly transform the most beautifully designed typography into code? With both roles knowing the basics, we’ll be able to start contributing to a better web by producing better web typography. Together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important things in typography is to shape a seamless reading experience that invites the reader and presents the content in an objective way. To do that, we need to be able to shape perfect paragraphs. There are three keys to doing that, as Josef Mueller-Brockmann—a renowned 20th-century typographer and visual communicator, put it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The reader should be able to read the message of a text easily and comfortably. This depends to a not inconsiderable extent on the size of the type, the length of the lines and the leading (line-height).&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Josef Mueller–Brockmann&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Equilateral triangle of a perfect paragraph article was originally published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/equilateral-triangle-perfect-paragraph/&quot;&gt;CSS-Tricks&lt;/a&gt; where you can read the rest. I launched a learning game based on this theory at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/triangle-game.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that as many people as possible come across this game and learn that line-height, font-size, and length of lines always need to be considered together. Try to get the best result and challenge your friends. The more people know about this, the better the web typography will get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com/triangle&quot;&gt;Check out the game here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Typography" /><category term="Web-design" /><summary type="html">And the lack of knowledge about typography doesn’t come from ignorance. I learned that web designers are commonly either self-taught and haven’t grasped the importance of typography yet, or they actually studied design but typography was just one of the classes they had to attend.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting things done with Trello</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/articles/2017/04/30/getting-things-done-with-trello/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting things done with Trello" /><published>2017-04-30T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2017-04-30T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/articles/2017/04/30/getting-things-done-with-trello</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/articles/2017/04/30/getting-things-done-with-trello/">&lt;p&gt;Most people will enjoy the nice weather or take a trip. I use this precious time to do some work on my projects. Sounds dull, but deep down it makes me happy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Better Web Type has been on my to-do list for almost two years. Mostly because I didn’t know what to do and where to&amp;nbsp;start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I launched a project called &lt;a href=&quot;https://betterwebtype.com&quot;&gt;Better Web Type&lt;/a&gt; in February and my new website shortly after that. Better Web Type is an email course I wanted to do for a while but never really took the time. It required a lot of work and that was one of the reasons why I kept postponing it. Then I learned what are the best ways to move projects forward. It boils down to three things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Break big problems down into small chunks that are easier to solve,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put a deadline to all these small steps,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Always have an overview of progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trello, for me, plays an essential role in this process. I use it for both, my personal projects and my personal/professional development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-trello-for-personalprojects&quot;&gt;Using Trello for personal projects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each project gets its own board in Trello. Each board has four columns: Ideas, To Do, Doing, Done. The ‘Ideas’ column helps me a lot when it comes to quickly putting down, well, ideas. I have the Trello app on my iPhone so I can put something there anytime. Most of my ideas come out of the blue so that’s the best way for me to capture them. If I decide at some point that an idea won’t make it, I simply archive it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trello-01-board.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The cards should form a shape of a “bridge”. I always try to keep only one card in To Do and Doing columns.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The cards should form a shape of a “bridge”. I always try to keep only one card in To Do and Doing columns. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to making a Kan Ban system (which Trello in its essence is) work, is to keep things moving and staying lean. Don’t have too many things in the ‘To Do’ and ‘Doing’ columns. If something gets stuck in there it needs to get unstuck and moved forwards (or in some cases even backwards). I always try to have only one item in each of those columns. This way I can see what I’m working on at the moment and what’s the thing that comes next. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro tip: if an item is stuck in one of these two columns for too long but you’re not sure why, try to break it down into smaller tasks. Move some of them backwards if necessary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last is the ‘Done’ column. It seems completely unnecessary to have that column there at first. But what I found out is that it helps with motivation. When there’s hard things that need to be done and you’re starting to despair, a list, full of tasks that were already completed show that you really can do anything. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-trello-for-personalprofessional-development&quot;&gt;Using Trello for personal/professional development&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know how an where to draw the line between the personal and professional development. Almost everything I do in free time helps with my professional development and I enjoy doing what I do anyway. I guess it’s the same question as when it comes to work/life balance. It’s not even a question when work is fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trello-02-planning.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My ‘Planning’ board is made of short term (ST) and long term (LT) plans cards.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;My ‘Planning’ board is made of short term (ST) and long term (LT) plans cards. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the basic—To Do, Doing and Done columns for this. The trick here is that I have two types of cards. One for long term and one for short, long term for a year and short for the current quarter. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long term card gets a name like ‘LT—2017’ and it’s there that I write down the things that I want to do in the current year, broken down into quarters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trello-03-card.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My LT plan card consists of a broad plan for the current year, split into quarters.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;My LT plan card consists of a broad plan for the current year, split into quarters. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This description is then followed by a number of checklists. Ticking things in these lists helps me with motivation again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short term card is more detailed. It has checklists for things I want to read, projects I want to do, articles and newsletters I want to write and skills I want to work on in the current quarter. For example, in this quarter (April–June), I want to read five books, work on various Better Web Type projects and write a couple of articles. This newsletter is also in the list of things I planned for this quarter. As you see in the screenshot, there’s no skills that I plan working on in this quarter. In the past I had things like completing the React.js and Python courses there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trello-04-card-details.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The short term card is mostly made of checklists of things I want to do in the upcoming 3 months.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The short term card is mostly made of checklists of things I want to do in the upcoming 3 months. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;moving-thingsforward&quot;&gt;Moving things forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing in completing projects is moving things forward. As I said, Trello plays a key role in that for me but Trello alone isn’t enough. I figured that out a while ago. I had things broken down into small steps and planned but kept failing at actually completing them. Then I found out how important it is to 1. have a deadline for every small thing in the ‘To Do’ list and 2. have a constant overview over the progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things help me with this. At work, I have a small notebook where I write down the todos for each week. Every morning when I come in I check that list and decide what I’ll work on that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trello-05-notebook.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My to dos for the week 13.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;My to dos for the week 13. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At home, I have a whiteboard where I do a similar thing. I have a weekly to do list but I also write down all the small steps that need to be done for a project and put a date next to them. It’s not so much about meeting the deadline. It’s more about putting a sense of urgency to the tasks. Urgency that is commonly not there when we work on personal projects. A deadline will push you to do things, even if you have to move it for a week or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/trello-06-whiteboard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The whiteboard wall at home keeps reminding me of things that need to be done, by when and motivates me at the same time.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The whiteboard wall at home keeps reminding me of things that need to be done, by when and motivates me at the same time. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not sure if you noticed it but I don’t have deadlines next to my tasks in the notebook at work. That’s exactly because of that sense of urgency. There’s no lack of that at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The overview of the progress is essential. Before, I had these tasks written down in Trello but it was so easy to forget about them. Now I have them where I can’t miss them. I check the notepad at work every day and I can’t not see the big whiteboard I have at home. These help me remind of things that need to be done everyday and motivates me when I see things that have already been completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does it work with Trello? I usually have the top-level description of the task in Trello and the small steps required to complete it on my whiteboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-thingsdone&quot;&gt;Getting things done&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m really happy that I managed to perfect my working process like that. It took me a while to figure it out but now I’m finally in a place where I manage to get my personal projects through the door. They’re not just an idea I want to work on at some time. They’re turned into a series of small steps that don’t seem scary and get done by a specific date.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="articles" /><category term="Productivity" /><category term="Day-to-day" /><summary type="html">Most people will enjoy the nice weather or take a trip. I use this precious time to do some work on my projects. Sounds dull, but deep down it makes me happy. </summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Putting up a wall</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/01/13/putting-up-a-wall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Putting up a wall" /><published>2017-01-13T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-13T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/01/13/putting-up-a-wall</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/01/13/putting-up-a-wall/">&lt;p&gt;And that’s alright because that was a huge part of their empire. They swore to themselves never to let their guard down after Rome was sacked by the Gauls in its early history. Because of that, they developed a highly organised, professional war machine. They conquered whatever they set their sights on. And they remained hungry — after each conquest they already had plans for the next one. At their peak, the Romans controlled the region between the frozen Scottish highlands in the north and the sandy deserts of north Africa in the south. But then — they stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emperor Hadrian decided to put up walls to “protect the empire”. His decision meant that he was happy with what he had. Protecting his lands became more important than conquering new ones. It was a drastic shift in mentality. A mentality that Romans never adopted before. Until then, they were always on the offensive, expanding further into unknown. The more they conquered, the more resources they had to expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, all of a sudden, they decided to put this war machine on hold. They put their legions on the walls where, for most of the time, they waited. The most effective army in the world was put on a defensive. They couldn’t use their skills so often anymore and they didn’t have to learn new ones to overcome new obstacles. The decline of the army started. The sharp swords got dull. The tactics were forgotten. A few generations later, it was nowhere near the might of the early empire. The downfall had started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-put-up-a-wall-draw-aline&quot;&gt;Don’t put up a wall, draw a line&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we can learn from this story is that we should never put up our walls. We should never draw the line and be happy with what we have. I don’t mean that in a materialistic way. Money and materialism are the worst things to drive someone forward. Look beyond that and see what you want to achieve. Are you looking for knowledge to satisfy your hunger of curiosity? Are you looking to pick up skills that will always keep you sharp — in step with time? The moment you put up that wall will be the moment of the start of your decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put up a wall once. I was in the middle of transitioning from web design to UI &amp;amp; visual design and I thought to myself: it’s my job to make this look nice, I don’t want to worry about coding it. That’s developer’s job. I was happy with my UI &amp;amp; visual design skills so I put up a wall around them. My ignorance turned into fear. Fear of code and anything about it. I had basic web design skills from before but started neglecting them. JavaScript was what I dreaded the most. I had always relied on my brother, who’s a full stack developer, whenever I needed anything done in Javascript or jQuery. Even if it was a simple animated scroll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then one day, out of the blue, I decided it was time to change. I tore that wall down. It happened in an instant. I decided that my skills weren’t good enough as they were. I finally decided to face my fear. I started learning JavaScript. I completed the course on Codecademy. I read a book. I started coding and exploring what I can do with my newly acquired skill. I conquered my fear. I broke trough the wall and the only thing that I had on my mind was: “okay, what’s next?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through conquering that fear, I rediscovered my hunger. My curiosity. My mind shifted. Now I feel like there’s nothing that I can’t do. The opposite. I can do anything I put my mind to. It may need more time at first but I will do it. Now I don’t put up walls anymore. I draw lines. These lines don’t represent the current state. They don’t represent something that I’m happy with. They represent a point in the future. They represents skills I want to acquire, products I want to build and the person I want to be. Lines can be moved. Walls can’t.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">And that’s alright because that was a huge part of their empire. They swore to themselves never to let their guard down after Rome was sacked by the Gauls in its early history. Because of that, they developed a highly organised, professional war machine. They conquered whatever they set their sights on. And they remained hungry — after each conquest they already had plans for the next one. At their peak, the Romans controlled the region between the frozen Scottish highlands in the north and the sandy deserts of north Africa in the south. But then — they stopped.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A two-step, no bullshit guide to sketching</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/12/08/a-two-step-no-bullshit-guide-to-sketching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A two-step, no bullshit guide to sketching" /><published>2016-12-08T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-08T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/12/08/a-two-step-no-bullshit-guide-to-sketching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/12/08/a-two-step-no-bullshit-guide-to-sketching/">&lt;p&gt;In the last dispatch I wrote about my story of how I learned that &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect/&quot;&gt;sketches aren’t meant to be perfect&lt;/a&gt;. How they aren’t meant to give final answers. They’re meant to ask further questions. To doubt your own solutions. And with that comes a lot more sketching. Sketching is not something you do at the start of the process, produce a wonderful looking sketch and move on. Sketching needs to be done throughout the design process. And in order to produce more sketches quicker, the quality of sketching needs to move aside. Here’s quick overview of my sketching kit followed by a few tips to make sketching serve its true meaning in your design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sketching-kit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My sketch kit: A Schneider Topliner 967, a Sharpie and a shader.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;My sketch kit: A Schneider Topliner 967, a Sharpie and a shader. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;start-with-a-sharpie&quot;&gt;Start with a sharpie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some designers will use a pencil to start drawing their early sketches. They do so because their ideas aren’t clear yet. So they draw an interface, see it’s not right, erase parts of it and draw them again. This is a great way to start spending too much time on one sketch only and start thinking about details way too early. My recommendation is don’t use a pencil and an eraser. Use a sharpie instead. Or something similar, as long as the tip of the pen is thick and will produce thick lines. This will force you to not focus on details and to make mistakes. Mistakes that you can’t erase. So to fix a mistake you have to draw a new version of the sketch. I know, you’re probably thinking: “but that’s a waste of time!” Here’s the tricky part. These early sketches should be so simple that it takes you very little time to produce. By little time I mean less than a minute. If it’s not the right solution you just discard it without feeling sorry for wasting effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, it’s important that you try to explore different ideas, solutions, combinations of different UI elements and interactions. Once you have that in front of you, you’ll start seeing patterns and connections that you couldn’t see before. You might want to try and combine a few sketches into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro tip: try to sketch on a large canvas like a big paper, a whiteboard or a even a wall. Don’t use a small notepad. This will make you even faster and you’ll have a nice overview of your progress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/early-sketches.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A total of 6 different sketches were explored in this particular process (as seen here with my notes on stickies).&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A total of 6 different sketches were explored in this particular process (as seen here with my notes on stickies). &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;converge-and-add-some-details&quot;&gt;Converge and add (some) details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be more comfortable with what you produced through sketching at this point. You’ve explored different ideas, layouts, UI elements… You might have combined some of them already and there’s probably a version of the sketch or two that you think might be the right ones. But there’s still lots of questions. It’s time to draw a bit more detailed sketches. Here’s where my Schindler and shader pens come in. The title that was just a wavy line before now becomes actual text. The paragraphs are still wavy lines. The UI elements become more detailed as well. The button is not just a dark box, it’s a box with text and some shading. You might even add some (basic) representations of icons at this point. It’s ok to spend more time on these sketches. It’s ok because you’ve already answered a lot of questions. At this point, the only way to start answering more questions is to add details. And it’s ok to do so because you narrowed down your solution to one or two sketches earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/final-sketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Final result with a bit more details and shading. Still not a pretty sketch, but it does the job.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Final result with a bit more details and shading. Still not a pretty sketch, but it does the job. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">In the last dispatch I wrote about my story of how I learned that sketches aren’t meant to be perfect. How they aren’t meant to give final answers. They’re meant to ask further questions. To doubt your own solutions. And with that comes a lot more sketching. Sketching is not something you do at the start of the process, produce a wonderful looking sketch and move on. Sketching needs to be done throughout the design process. And in order to produce more sketches quicker, the quality of sketching needs to move aside. Here’s quick overview of my sketching kit followed by a few tips to make sketching serve its true meaning in your design process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My sketches aren’t perfect</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My sketches aren’t perfect" /><published>2016-11-03T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-03T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect/">&lt;p&gt;This means that I started to sketch a lot more. I always loved to sketch, scribble and draw. I always felt this need to put something on the paper. Something visual I can refer to later on. Something I put out of my head—an idea that gets transformed into something physical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember a particular time when I was looking for some inspiration and stumbled upon this sketch. The effect it had on me was the opposite of what I was looking for. It didn’t inspire me. It demotivated me. My sketches were never made of straight lines, shading and nice depictions of people, maps and UI elements. My sketches were ugly, with lots of corrections, lines that were too long, boxes that were too small. If someone took a look at them they wouldn’t be able to understand a thing without my explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sketches-arent-supposed-to-be-perfect&quot;&gt;Sketches aren’t supposed to be perfect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s the thing about sketches. There’s a secret that not a lot of designers know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fundamental thing about sketching is that it is about asking not telling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Bill Buxton&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sketches don’t have to tell anything to anyone else but yourself. Even then, they’re merely a tool to ask further questions. By asking further questions we get to asking the right questions. Eventually. And only if you ask yourself enough questions. This means, a lot of sketching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of sketching is not to do a perfect sketch that looks awesome. It’s not for sharing information with others. It’s for putting an idea to the paper. For me personally, it’s one of the three magic moments in the design process. By drawing one sketch that looks more like a drawing, designers miss the main purpose of sketching. To depict an idea as it is currently in your head—with all the holes that represent the missing information. By drawing as many sketches as possible and putting as many ideas from your head to paper we get in the right mindset and start to discover the missing parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you want to sketch something, don’t pay any attention to what your sketch looks like. Instead, try to produce as many as possible—different ideas, multiple possible solutions our different combinations of UI elements. Your job shouldn’t be assessed based on your sketches. It’s the final product that we need to focus on. You sketches need to be something that you can throw away if it’s not what you need. It’s something that you spend minutes drawing instead of hours. It’s something that will take you from a cloud of ideas to a functioning product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might even argue that sketching is a complete waste of time and should be skipped altogether. It either takes too long or it’s done very quickly. Both arguments serve as a good excuse to do so. I mentioned earlier that I think sketching is one of the three magic moments in the design process (I’ll write about these at some time). Sketching is the most important one. Your idea takes form for the first time and makes everything clearer. It’s not a perfect representation of what you want to do but this is where the magic of sketching lies. They can, should and will change through time. The quicker they change, the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">This means that I started to sketch a lot more. I always loved to sketch, scribble and draw. I always felt this need to put something on the paper. Something visual I can refer to later on. Something I put out of my head—an idea that gets transformed into something physical.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You are not who you think you are</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/13/you-are-not-who-you-think-you-are/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You are not who you think you are" /><published>2016-10-13T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-13T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/13/you-are-not-who-you-think-you-are</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/13/you-are-not-who-you-think-you-are/">&lt;p&gt;“Sign here and you’ll resign from the technical high school”, said the headmaster as he gave me a disappointed look. It was the resignation letter. I had no choice but sign it. I had skipped way too many classes. I went over the limit and this was the next step in the process. But it wasn’t just about skipping classes. I wasn’t doing well at school at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone was surprised by how my first years of high school went. Until then I never had problems in school. In fact, school never really posed a challenge to me. All I needed to do to get trough the year was a minimal effort. The first year of high school followed a similar fashion. No major problems, completed with minimal effort. Some trouble would arise occasionally but nothing too serious. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class teacher figured me out though. She noticed that I’m not investing enough time in school matters and that I could be doing a lot better if I did. Soon she would start to label me as lazy. She literally called me “lazy boy” (she taught English). She did that publicly. Maybe it was her way of trying to wake me up and motivate me. Well, it didn’t work. Quite the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matej-is-clever-butlazy&quot;&gt;Matej is clever but lazy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being publicly labeled as lazy made things worse. My schoolmates treated me as such and other teachers as well. “Matej is clever but he’s lazy” is what they would say about me. And that triggered the opposite effect of what they wanted to achieve. It made me care about school even less. I had less problems with skipping classes. I eventually failed a year and dropped out soon after that. I was already perceived as a failure so why not act as one as well? It may sound stupid but that’s how people work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an experiment conducted in India. The students from different castes had to take a test. They were split into two groups—one that had to publicly tell what caste they’re from and another where the students didn’t have to do that. The students from the lower castes in the first group performed worse than the students from the higher caste but their lower caste colleagues performed the same as the ones from the higher caste in the other group. This means that the lower caste students that had to publicly disclose their caste subconsciously felt that they had to perform worse than the ones from the higher caste so they did. We are not who we think we are. We are what the environment and the society we live in dictate us to be. You can read more about the experiment here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing with me was… I wasn’t lazy at all. I just didn’t care enough. I preferred playing video games day in day out. Red Alert 2, Half-Life, Quake 3 Arena… you name it, I played it. The time I skipped an annoying class to go home early with a bag of candy and play video games was the time of my life. Besides, when I wasn’t playing video games I was coding and designing websites. More for fun than anything else but as it turned out, it was these skills that took me places, not the ones I learned in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not who you think you are. I am not who I think I am. We are defined by so many factors and the society is a large part of it. But if we acknowledge that, we might be able to regain our identities. Maybe just a small part. So… who are you?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Psychology" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">“Sign here and you’ll resign from the technical high school”, said the headmaster as he gave me a disappointed look. It was the resignation letter. I had no choice but sign it. I had skipped way too many classes. I went over the limit and this was the next step in the process. But it wasn’t just about skipping classes. I wasn’t doing well at school at all.</summary></entry></feed>
