<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-03-17T20:18:26+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Matej Latin</title><subtitle>Matej Latin is a UX/UI deisgner working for Auto Trader UK in London. He writes about design, minimalism and typography.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Putting up a wall</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/01/13/putting-up-a-wall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Putting up a wall" /><published>2017-01-13T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-13T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/01/13/putting-up-a-wall</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2017/01/13/putting-up-a-wall/">&lt;p&gt;And that’s alright because that was a huge part of their empire. They swore to themselves never to let their guard down after Rome was sacked by the Gauls in its early history. Because of that, they developed a highly organised, professional war machine. They conquered whatever they set their sights on. And they remained hungry — after each conquest they already had plans for the next one. At their peak, the Romans controlled the region between the frozen Scottish highlands in the north and the sandy deserts of north Africa in the south. But then — they stopped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emperor Hadrian decided to put up walls to “protect the empire”. His decision meant that he was happy with what he had. Protecting his lands became more important than conquering new ones. It was a drastic shift in mentality. A mentality that Romans never adopted before. Until then, they were always on the offensive, expanding further into unknown. The more they conquered, the more resources they had to expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, all of a sudden, they decided to put this war machine on hold. They put their legions on the walls where, for most of the time, they waited. The most effective army in the world was put on a defensive. They couldn’t use their skills so often anymore and they didn’t have to learn new ones to overcome new obstacles. The decline of the army started. The sharp swords got dull. The tactics were forgotten. A few generations later, it was nowhere near the might of the early empire. The downfall had started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-put-up-a-wall-draw-aline&quot;&gt;Don’t put up a wall, draw a line&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we can learn from this story is that we should never put up our walls. We should never draw the line and be happy with what we have. I don’t mean that in a materialistic way. Money and materialism are the worst things to drive someone forward. Look beyond that and see what you want to achieve. Are you looking for knowledge to satisfy your hunger of curiosity? Are you looking to pick up skills that will always keep you sharp — in step with time? The moment you put up that wall will be the moment of the start of your decline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put up a wall once. I was in the middle of transitioning from web design to UI &amp;amp; visual design and I thought to myself: it’s my job to make this look nice, I don’t want to worry about coding it. That’s developer’s job. I was happy with my UI &amp;amp; visual design skills so I put up a wall around them. My ignorance turned into fear. Fear of code and anything about it. I had basic web design skills from before but started neglecting them. JavaScript was what I dreaded the most. I had always relied on my brother, who’s a full stack developer, whenever I needed anything done in Javascript or jQuery. Even if it was a simple animated scroll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then one day, out of the blue, I decided it was time to change. I tore that wall down. It happened in an instant. I decided that my skills weren’t good enough as they were. I finally decided to face my fear. I started learning JavaScript. I completed the course on Codecademy. I read a book. I started coding and exploring what I can do with my newly acquired skill. I conquered my fear. I broke trough the wall and the only thing that I had on my mind was: “okay, what’s next?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through conquering that fear, I rediscovered my hunger. My curiosity. My mind shifted. Now I feel like there’s nothing that I can’t do. The opposite. I can do anything I put my mind to. It may need more time at first but I will do it. Now I don’t put up walls anymore. I draw lines. These lines don’t represent the current state. They don’t represent something that I’m happy with. They represent a point in the future. They represents skills I want to acquire, products I want to build and the person I want to be. Lines can be moved. Walls can’t.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">And that’s alright because that was a huge part of their empire. They swore to themselves never to let their guard down after Rome was sacked by the Gauls in its early history. Because of that, they developed a highly organised, professional war machine. They conquered whatever they set their sights on. And they remained hungry — after each conquest they already had plans for the next one. At their peak, the Romans controlled the region between the frozen Scottish highlands in the north and the sandy deserts of north Africa in the south. But then — they stopped.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A two-step, no bullshit guide to sketching</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/12/08/a-two-step-no-bullshit-guide-to-sketching/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A two-step, no bullshit guide to sketching" /><published>2016-12-08T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-08T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/12/08/a-two-step-no-bullshit-guide-to-sketching</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/12/08/a-two-step-no-bullshit-guide-to-sketching/">&lt;p&gt;In the last dispatch I wrote about my story of how I learned that &lt;a href=&quot;/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect/&quot;&gt;sketches aren’t meant to be perfect&lt;/a&gt;. How they aren’t meant to give final answers. They’re meant to ask further questions. To doubt your own solutions. And with that comes a lot more sketching. Sketching is not something you do at the start of the process, produce a wonderful looking sketch and move on. Sketching needs to be done throughout the design process. And in order to produce more sketches quicker, the quality of sketching needs to move aside. Here’s quick overview of my sketching kit followed by a few tips to make sketching serve its true meaning in your design process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/sketching-kit.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My sketch kit: A Schneider Topliner 967, a Sharpie and a shader.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;My sketch kit: A Schneider Topliner 967, a Sharpie and a shader. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;start-with-a-sharpie&quot;&gt;Start with a sharpie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some designers will use a pencil to start drawing their early sketches. They do so because their ideas aren’t clear yet. So they draw an interface, see it’s not right, erase parts of it and draw them again. This is a great way to start spending too much time on one sketch only and start thinking about details way too early. My recommendation is don’t use a pencil and an eraser. Use a sharpie instead. Or something similar, as long as the tip of the pen is thick and will produce thick lines. This will force you to not focus on details and to make mistakes. Mistakes that you can’t erase. So to fix a mistake you have to draw a new version of the sketch. I know, you’re probably thinking: “but that’s a waste of time!” Here’s the tricky part. These early sketches should be so simple that it takes you very little time to produce. By little time I mean less than a minute. If it’s not the right solution you just discard it without feeling sorry for wasting effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage, it’s important that you try to explore different ideas, solutions, combinations of different UI elements and interactions. Once you have that in front of you, you’ll start seeing patterns and connections that you couldn’t see before. You might want to try and combine a few sketches into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Pro tip: try to sketch on a large canvas like a big paper, a whiteboard or a even a wall. Don’t use a small notepad. This will make you even faster and you’ll have a nice overview of your progress.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/early-sketches.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A total of 6 different sketches were explored in this particular process (as seen here with my notes on stickies).&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A total of 6 different sketches were explored in this particular process (as seen here with my notes on stickies). &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;converge-and-add-some-details&quot;&gt;Converge and add (some) details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should be more comfortable with what you produced through sketching at this point. You’ve explored different ideas, layouts, UI elements… You might have combined some of them already and there’s probably a version of the sketch or two that you think might be the right ones. But there’s still lots of questions. It’s time to draw a bit more detailed sketches. Here’s where my Schindler and shader pens come in. The title that was just a wavy line before now becomes actual text. The paragraphs are still wavy lines. The UI elements become more detailed as well. The button is not just a dark box, it’s a box with text and some shading. You might even add some (basic) representations of icons at this point. It’s ok to spend more time on these sketches. It’s ok because you’ve already answered a lot of questions. At this point, the only way to start answering more questions is to add details. And it’s ok to do so because you narrowed down your solution to one or two sketches earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/final-sketch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Final result with a bit more details and shading. Still not a pretty sketch, but it does the job.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Final result with a bit more details and shading. Still not a pretty sketch, but it does the job. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">In the last dispatch I wrote about my story of how I learned that sketches aren’t meant to be perfect. How they aren’t meant to give final answers. They’re meant to ask further questions. To doubt your own solutions. And with that comes a lot more sketching. Sketching is not something you do at the start of the process, produce a wonderful looking sketch and move on. Sketching needs to be done throughout the design process. And in order to produce more sketches quicker, the quality of sketching needs to move aside. Here’s quick overview of my sketching kit followed by a few tips to make sketching serve its true meaning in your design process.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My sketches aren’t perfect</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My sketches aren’t perfect" /><published>2016-11-03T19:56:54+00:00</published><updated>2016-11-03T19:56:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/11/03/my-sketches-arent-perfect/">&lt;p&gt;This means that I started to sketch a lot more. I always loved to sketch, scribble and draw. I always felt this need to put something on the paper. Something visual I can refer to later on. Something I put out of my head—an idea that gets transformed into something physical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember a particular time when I was looking for some inspiration and stumbled upon this sketch. The effect it had on me was the opposite of what I was looking for. It didn’t inspire me. It demotivated me. My sketches were never made of straight lines, shading and nice depictions of people, maps and UI elements. My sketches were ugly, with lots of corrections, lines that were too long, boxes that were too small. If someone took a look at them they wouldn’t be able to understand a thing without my explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sketches-arent-supposed-to-be-perfect&quot;&gt;Sketches aren’t supposed to be perfect&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that’s the thing about sketches. There’s a secret that not a lot of designers know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fundamental thing about sketching is that it is about asking not telling.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;cite&gt;—&amp;hairsp;Bill Buxton&lt;/cite&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your sketches don’t have to tell anything to anyone else but yourself. Even then, they’re merely a tool to ask further questions. By asking further questions we get to asking the right questions. Eventually. And only if you ask yourself enough questions. This means, a lot of sketching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of sketching is not to do a perfect sketch that looks awesome. It’s not for sharing information with others. It’s for putting an idea to the paper. For me personally, it’s one of the three magic moments in the design process. By drawing one sketch that looks more like a drawing, designers miss the main purpose of sketching. To depict an idea as it is currently in your head—with all the holes that represent the missing information. By drawing as many sketches as possible and putting as many ideas from your head to paper we get in the right mindset and start to discover the missing parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you want to sketch something, don’t pay any attention to what your sketch looks like. Instead, try to produce as many as possible—different ideas, multiple possible solutions our different combinations of UI elements. Your job shouldn’t be assessed based on your sketches. It’s the final product that we need to focus on. You sketches need to be something that you can throw away if it’s not what you need. It’s something that you spend minutes drawing instead of hours. It’s something that will take you from a cloud of ideas to a functioning product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might even argue that sketching is a complete waste of time and should be skipped altogether. It either takes too long or it’s done very quickly. Both arguments serve as a good excuse to do so. I mentioned earlier that I think sketching is one of the three magic moments in the design process (I’ll write about these at some time). Sketching is the most important one. Your idea takes form for the first time and makes everything clearer. It’s not a perfect representation of what you want to do but this is where the magic of sketching lies. They can, should and will change through time. The quicker they change, the better.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">This means that I started to sketch a lot more. I always loved to sketch, scribble and draw. I always felt this need to put something on the paper. Something visual I can refer to later on. Something I put out of my head—an idea that gets transformed into something physical.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You are not who you think you are</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/13/you-are-not-who-you-think-you-are/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You are not who you think you are" /><published>2016-10-13T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-13T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/13/you-are-not-who-you-think-you-are</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/13/you-are-not-who-you-think-you-are/">&lt;p&gt;“Sign here and you’ll resign from the technical high school”, said the headmaster as he gave me a disappointed look. It was the resignation letter. I had no choice but sign it. I had skipped way too many classes. I went over the limit and this was the next step in the process. But it wasn’t just about skipping classes. I wasn’t doing well at school at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone was surprised by how my first years of high school went. Until then I never had problems in school. In fact, school never really posed a challenge to me. All I needed to do to get trough the year was a minimal effort. The first year of high school followed a similar fashion. No major problems, completed with minimal effort. Some trouble would arise occasionally but nothing too serious. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The class teacher figured me out though. She noticed that I’m not investing enough time in school matters and that I could be doing a lot better if I did. Soon she would start to label me as lazy. She literally called me “lazy boy” (she taught English). She did that publicly. Maybe it was her way of trying to wake me up and motivate me. Well, it didn’t work. Quite the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;matej-is-clever-butlazy&quot;&gt;Matej is clever but lazy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being publicly labeled as lazy made things worse. My schoolmates treated me as such and other teachers as well. “Matej is clever but he’s lazy” is what they would say about me. And that triggered the opposite effect of what they wanted to achieve. It made me care about school even less. I had less problems with skipping classes. I eventually failed a year and dropped out soon after that. I was already perceived as a failure so why not act as one as well? It may sound stupid but that’s how people work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an experiment conducted in India. The students from different castes had to take a test. They were split into two groups—one that had to publicly tell what caste they’re from and another where the students didn’t have to do that. The students from the lower castes in the first group performed worse than the students from the higher caste but their lower caste colleagues performed the same as the ones from the higher caste in the other group. This means that the lower caste students that had to publicly disclose their caste subconsciously felt that they had to perform worse than the ones from the higher caste so they did. We are not who we think we are. We are what the environment and the society we live in dictate us to be. You can read more about the experiment here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing with me was… I wasn’t lazy at all. I just didn’t care enough. I preferred playing video games day in day out. Red Alert 2, Half-Life, Quake 3 Arena… you name it, I played it. The time I skipped an annoying class to go home early with a bag of candy and play video games was the time of my life. Besides, when I wasn’t playing video games I was coding and designing websites. More for fun than anything else but as it turned out, it was these skills that took me places, not the ones I learned in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are not who you think you are. I am not who I think I am. We are defined by so many factors and the society is a large part of it. But if we acknowledge that, we might be able to regain our identities. Maybe just a small part. So… who are you?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Psychology" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">“Sign here and you’ll resign from the technical high school”, said the headmaster as he gave me a disappointed look. It was the resignation letter. I had no choice but sign it. I had skipped way too many classes. I went over the limit and this was the next step in the process. But it wasn’t just about skipping classes. I wasn’t doing well at school at all.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Faster horses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/04/faster-horses/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Faster horses" /><published>2016-10-04T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-04T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/04/faster-horses</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/10/04/faster-horses/">&lt;div class=&quot;conversation&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p class=&quot;indent&quot;&gt;“If I had asked people what they wanted, they would have said faster horses” is a quote attributed to Henry Ford. It’s a quote that many people use as an excuse not to do user testing. Because designers and product managers are supposed to be these geniuses that pull ideas out of thin air. Steve Jobs was one of those design/product gurus. All the designer and product manager wannabes have a quote or two from Steve that they hold close to their heart so they feel more secure about themselves. But neither Steve or Henry became famous for their ideas because they would be original. They weren’t. Steve didn’t make the first computer and Henry didn’t make the first car (he made the first car assembly line).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever someone quotes one of these guys, they try to convince other people in the room that it’s a designer’s job to know what the users want and need. But if there’s no research and no interaction with (potential) customers, how is a designer supposed to know that? It’s not that designers design products for themselves. And if they do, they’re probably not that good at designing anyway. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a very recent case where we were working on redesigning a product at Auto Trader we conducted some quick user testing with the people from our company. Some people suggested not to do that because the quality of the feedback will be low. They’re too invested in the product and know too much about it. Supposedly. We went on and did some testing anyway. We told them what the scenario was and what we want them to do. We were testing the UX of the new product and the UIs of some of the screens that were redesigned. A basic clickable wireframe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot of research done before we started working on redesigning the product and we didn’t expect to learn much. We were looking for a validation of what we had. But the people that we tested with started coming up with questions. “How do I buy a new car from this page?”, “Where can I see how long the car dealer has been in business?” etc. This were the questions that people haven’t asked until that point. We then explored why they were asking these questions and quickly went back to the drawing board. We updated the clickable wireframe and tested with a few more people. They had the same questions but this time they found the answers. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People don’t know what they want. That’s true. But they’ll know when something is missing. And you don’t want your product to be a bunch of features that completely miss what users want to do. Designers don’t know what people want. It’s not your job as a designer to know that by default. But it is your job to find out. If you’re designing for them, you have to know what their motivations are. Period. It’s not about the faster horses. It’s about the whys behind the faster horses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">“If I had asked people what they wanted, they would have said faster horses” is a quote attributed to Henry Ford. It’s a quote that many people use as an excuse not to do user testing. Because designers and product managers are supposed to be these geniuses that pull ideas out of thin air. Steve Jobs was one of those design/product gurus. All the designer and product manager wannabes have a quote or two from Steve that they hold close to their heart so they feel more secure about themselves. But neither Steve or Henry became famous for their ideas because they would be original. They weren’t. Steve didn’t make the first computer and Henry didn’t make the first car (he made the first car assembly line).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking through a creative block</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/09/21/breaking-through-a-creative-block/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking through a creative block" /><published>2016-09-21T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-09-21T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/09/21/breaking-through-a-creative-block</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/09/21/breaking-through-a-creative-block/">&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you know these moments too. Working hard on something but not getting anywhere with it. Through all these years I found three approaches that help me through these moments. Most of the times they work. But sometimes they don’t and I ship average work, feel bad about it and can’t wait to get back and improve it. Anyway, here they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;force-my-way-through-with-hard-work&quot;&gt;Force my way through with hard work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many times have I spent hours of work on a project that needed to be done yesterday but still wasn’t going anywhere. The feeling of frustration grows until you’re fed up and need a break. I usually do take a break but a short one. The work needs to be done in a few hours and there’s nothing left but force my way through. A few hours of hard work after already a few hours of hard work is incredibly tough. But sometimes it’s all that is left. It may produce above average work at best but it will be done. It’s important to leave your perfectionism out of it when you need to take this approach. Momentum is the other important part. Don’t take long breaks. Take more shorter ones instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-on-something-else&quot;&gt;Work on something else&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach will only work if you have the luxury to postpone the work for a little while. Working on one thing for hours will narrow your focus and you won’t be able to see the big picture anymore. You might also need a different perspective on the work but after hours spent on it, you’re too heavily invested. You need to get away from the work and work on something else for a while. Spend an hour or even less trying to find a solution to another problem, then get back to the original task. You’ll fell slightly refreshed and more eager to continue the work. Smaller tasks are the best for intermediate shift of focus. Try to complete at least a few to motivate you even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sleep-on-it&quot;&gt;Sleep on it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last approach is not for the rushed projects that need to be done on the same day. This will only work if you can get back to work on another day but might be the most effective. Our subconscious mind is more effective at finding patterns than the conscious one. After spending hours of hard work on a problem your brain will do you a favour of trying to find a solution while you sleep. That’s why it’s much better to study for an exam before you go to sleep, not in the morning just before the exam (tell that to the young version of me). You’ll have a better picture of the problem you’re trying to solve and sometimes even a solution. This approach is great for tougher problems that need time. Others use this approach quite effectively as well. The key is that you need to spend a few hours working hard on the problem. Maybe just before you go to sleep as well. Then let your brain do the heavy lifting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">I’m sure you know these moments too. Working hard on something but not getting anywhere with it. Through all these years I found three approaches that help me through these moments. Most of the times they work. But sometimes they don’t and I ship average work, feel bad about it and can’t wait to get back and improve it. Anyway, here they are.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My reading process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/25/my-reading-process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My reading process" /><published>2016-08-25T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-08-25T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/25/my-reading-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/25/my-reading-process/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading-books&quot;&gt;Reading Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I keep a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/11006629-matej-latin-latin&quot;&gt;to-read list on Goodreads.com&lt;/a&gt;. Whenever I encounter a book that I find interesting, I add it to this list (more than 400 items at the moment). Besides reading I also like to plan. I use Trello for all my planning. I split every year into quarters—periods of three months. Then I write down all the books that I want to read in the upcoming period and create a checklist. With a goal of 40 books per year that’s 10 books per quarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the actual reading of the book. I always keep a pencil with me—when reading a book in physical form—to make notes. Simple underlining and marking with an exclamation mark does the trick. I never write actual notes. I may, sometimes, add small page indicator stickers to the page where I make a note. This way I can come back to it in just a few seconds. I tend to do that only with technical and detailed books. Especially the ones I know I’ll be coming back to in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reading-articles&quot;&gt;Reading Articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s so much content on the web. It’s hard to keep up with it and even daunting at times. I’m signed up to a few newsletters, some weekly, some daily. That’s where I find most of the content that I want to read online. I want reliable, high-quality content. So far, curated newsletters were the only ones that met my criteria. I tend to open a link from Twitter every now and then but I always take those with a pinch of salt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, whatever I find interesting goes to my to-read list. This one I keep at Instapaper. I never read these articles right after finding them. They always go to this list and I read them when I have time. Unlike for books, I don’t have a designated time for reading articles. It takes me 5–10 minutes to read most of them so they’re great for quick reads during snack time or something similar. I archive all the articles I read so the to-read list stays clean (kinda makes me feel good to have an almost empty to-read list).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weekly-reading-review&quot;&gt;Weekly Reading Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used to write book reviews. A short recap with a simple goal. Go through the book again and review my own notes and underlinings. I learned much more from a book this way than just reading it once. I would then publish these reviews on my website. The process was too long and because of that it failed its purpose. So I decided to keep doing that but keep these notes private. This way I can keep them quick and dirty but just enough so I can get back to them later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now do this in my “weekly reading review”—whenever I actually have time to have one. I sit down, take a look at the book and articles that I read that week. I focus on my notes and write a short recap. The recap is not even made of actual sentences. Bullet lists mostly. But it’s enough for me to be able to get back and just enough so what I read actually sticks in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this systematic process of reading to work well for me. Am I taking it too far? Do you have a similar approach to reading? Share your thoughts with me.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">Reading Books
First of all, I keep a to-read list on Goodreads.com. Whenever I encounter a book that I find interesting, I add it to this list (more than 400 items at the moment). Besides reading I also like to plan. I use Trello for all my planning. I split every year into quarters—periods of three months. Then I write down all the books that I want to read in the upcoming period and create a checklist. With a goal of 40 books per year that’s 10 books per quarter.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I quit design twice</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/18/i-quit-design-twice/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I quit design twice" /><published>2016-08-18T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-08-18T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/18/i-quit-design-twice</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/18/i-quit-design-twice/">&lt;p&gt;The last thing I remember I wanted to be was a “game designer/developer”. I just got my first PC and gaming was all I did. Then, at some point, I stopped thinking about what I really want to do. The life auto–pilot must have kicked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;aside&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I still look back on those years as the best years of my life. Video games, music and candy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/aside&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primary school was a piece of cake, high school was a wake up call. I spent most of my time playing video games, neglecting school assignments. I’d come home, turn on the PC and start playing Half-Life, Command &amp;amp; Conquer, Civilization. All these games were so time consuming. There was no time for anything else. My grades in school started to reflect this and I failed a class. The next year I dropped out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there was something else I used my PC for besides gaming. I was designing websites and setting up eCommerce sites for local clients. I picked up this interest as a kid but I had never thought it’d ever be anything more than a hobby. I was setting up WordPress blogs, Zen Cart web sites and drawing interfaces and websites in Photoshop by the time I finally finished high school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-to-get-serious&quot;&gt;Time to get serious&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After high school, just like almost anyone at my age, I went to study at a local university. “You’ll need a degree to have the slightest chances to get a job” was what everyone kept telling me. Ok, it’s probably time to get serious, is what I thought to myself. I decided to stop all the web design I had been doing and focus solely on studying. I enjoyed designing websites but it was time to quit. It was time to start focusing on what mattered in life: get a degree, get a job, earn money and everything will be alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;A degree → a “proper job” → money → everything’s alright&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a load of bullshit. I couldn’t stay away from designing websites. By that time, I wasn’t playing video games that much anymore. I unawarely started enjoying web design more. Studying didn’t suffer at all, as I finished top class. But now, I had to find a “proper” job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;getting-a-proper-job&quot;&gt;Getting a proper job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d just wrapped up studying and I was left with a degree that would secure me a good job. I actually believed that. But, nobody wanted a guy who was fresh from university. Finding a “proper” job proved impossible. At some point I just wanted to start working at a local electronics shop but even they didn’t want me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while, I finally got a job. It was the best job in the shit hole town where I come from. The best in terms of what a 25 year old guy, fresh from university could get. So I became a Business Process Manager at a local bank which is a part of a large, global group. I had been running my own company until that, doing what I always did—web design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I really had to quit design this time. The corporation where I worked at required me to do so. I wasn’t allowed to run my own company and be employed there at the same time. Alright, no problem with that. I got the best job around, it’s time to fully commit to it. Right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, life isn’t so easy and it certainly isn’t so simple. I hated my new job. I couldn’t stand working at that place. But what do I do? This is what I’m supposed to do right? Get a degree, check. Get a good, well paid job, check. Be happy, … hm…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I restarted doing web design work for clients a few months after I started working at that bank. It was the only thing that made me happy(er). I tried quitting twice but for some reason it stuck with me so I said to myself “fuck it, I’ll commit to it 100% this time”. I quit my well paid job and was going to freelance, just like I did before. I was presented with an opportunity to join Wondermags, a Luxembourgish startup, a week later. This was going to be my first in-house design role. Everything else is history. But it turned out well for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do what you love → Money → Everything’s alright&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson of my story: don’t quit what you’re good at. Especially if it makes you happy. Commit to it 100%, no matter what and everything will be alright. Forget everyone else. Forget the money. If you do what you love, the money will follow somehow. If anyone tells you otherwise, ignore them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX" /><category term="Design" /><summary type="html">The last thing I remember I wanted to be was a “game designer/developer”. I just got my first PC and gaming was all I did. Then, at some point, I stopped thinking about what I really want to do. The life auto–pilot must have kicked in.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">UX design is not what you think it is</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/11/ux-is-not/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="UX design is not what you think it is" /><published>2016-08-11T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-08-11T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/11/ux-is-not</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/08/11/ux-is-not/">&lt;p&gt;Let’s do a quick test. Go to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://adriengervaix.com/&quot;&gt;following website&lt;/a&gt;. Take a look around. Spend a minute or two on the site. Even a few if you wish. There is no particular information that you should be looking for no task. Already back? Cool. Now try to answer the following questions based on the information that you were able to get from that website. Don’t worry if you’re not a UX designer or a designer at all. In fact, that’s even better. Write down the answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is Adrien Gervaix and what does he do?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What specific project that he worked on do you remember? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Based on his case studies, what specific tasks does he do on a daily basis as a UX/UI designer?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Again, based on his case studies, what would you say UX design is?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done? Let me know your answers. I’d love to see your conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this quick test is the ever reinforced misconception of what UX and UX design is. I understand that people (like myself) are thought UX designers, UI designers, developers etc. And there’s no problem with that. thought people need a strong passion to drive them forward. But passion alone is not enough. There needs to be something or someone to guide them in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stop thinking about UX design as static, possibly beautifully designed wireframes and animations. Yes, UX is about wireframes and it is about animations. But it’s much more than that. It’s everything between a sketch on the paper and a fully working beautifully designed product that people enjoy using. They do so because it brings them value. Not because they enjoy the animations or pretty illustrations in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;floatRight&quot;&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Animations and a nice visual design can enhance a user experience but they alone can’t be one.&lt;/p&gt;
    
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adrien’s portfolio website looks great. Aesthetically, I love it! But Adrien has, as he explained here, spent months working on it, (possibly) without asking for feedback in the process. Not to mention that navigation (one of the key elements of UX) is broken and becomes a real pain in the ass after a minute of navigating through the site. Besides, the only UX tool he uses are wireframes. And even those are to pretty to serve their purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a website like that will get him lots of cool projects to work on but it won’t be the real kind of UX projects. And that’s bad for the company that he’ll work with, for him and for all the UX designers out there. Because it’s information like this that paints the wrong picture about what UX is. It’s so sad that even these days I still meet a lot of people, designers and non-designers alike, that think that what I do as a UX designer is wireframes and animations. Here’s an overview of what UX design truly is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/ux-overview.png&quot; alt=&quot;The elements of user experience&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The elements of user experience (&lt;a href=&quot;http://http://www.uxbeginner.com/ux-essentials-lesson-1-defining-user-experience-design/&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adrian may be early in his design career. And he really seems like a talented designer. But he’ll need to learn a lot more before he can call himself a UX designer. Don’t worry. I called myself a UX/UI designer way too early too. I did some wireframes and put visual designs on top of that. I thought I was doing UX work. Well… I wasn’t. I later learned that. I, just like a lot of designers out there, did that mistake. Don’t be one of them. Find out what UX really is. Join a course or at the very least, read a book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1867.The_Elements_of_User_Experience?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true&quot;&gt;The Elements of User Experience&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="UX" /><summary type="html">Let’s do a quick test. Go to the following website. Take a look around. Spend a minute or two on the site. Even a few if you wish. There is no particular information that you should be looking for no task. Already back? Cool. Now try to answer the following questions based on the information that you were able to get from that website. Don’t worry if you’re not a UX designer or a designer at all. In fact, that’s even better. Write down the answers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tab zero</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/07/21/tab-zero/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tab zero" /><published>2016-07-21T20:56:54+01:00</published><updated>2016-07-21T20:56:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/07/21/tab-zero</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/personal-notes/2016/07/21/tab-zero/">&lt;figure class=&quot;image&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/browser-tabs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Lots of tabs = chaos&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Lots of tabs = chaos &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be that guy. I wasn’t as extreme as most other people I see. I tried to keep the open tabs to a reasonable level, so I could still see a part of the title next to the icon. That was my minimum. But even that was driving me crazy. I would keep those tabs open just because I ‘stored’ an article that I wanted to read. I’d ‘store’ things that I’d probably find useful in the future. I’d ‘store’ pretty much everything like this (I gave up on bookmarks a long time ago).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I realised that all this ‘storing’ made me unproductive. The more I piled on this stored items, the less likely I was to return to it and actually use anything from it. How come? I had no idea back then. I just really disliked having so many things open. Waiting there for me to do something with it. It started to turn into a mental burden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more options we have, the less likely we’re to choose any of them—according to Barry Schwarz, the author of the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10639.The_Paradox_of_Choice?ac=1&amp;amp;from_search=true&quot;&gt;Paradox of Choice&lt;/a&gt;. People just aren’t good with making choices. All those ‘stored’ tabs presented options. Articles to read, things to use, videos to watch. The more I had ‘stored’, the less likely it was that I’d actually use anything ‘stored’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-tab-zero&quot;&gt;Enter Tab Zero&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve adopted the Inbox Zero strategy a while ago. It keeps my email tolerable and usable. If I have to do something with an email I leave it there until I do. If it’s done, I archive it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I don’t actually keep my inbox empty. I find extremisms like Inbox Zero more of a guidance than a rule. That’d become another tedious chore if I did. I don’t want that. So I came up with a similar strategy for keeping my open tabs to a minimum. I call it ‘Tab Zero’. Again, I don’t tend to close all the tabs in the browser—pinned tabs, for example, are open all the time (Trello, Confluence, Jira).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s an article I want to read but don’t have time, I save it to my Instapaper. If it’s something I want to share, I send it to Buffer. I find this to be liberating. A manageable number of tabs and storing other things where they actually have a place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, tools like Instapaper and Buffer help me keep those tabs to a minimum. The other problem with too many tabs being open is memory consumption. This had a major role in trying to solve my frustration with this problem. You know when Chrome crashes and you lose all those ‘stored’ items? I know. Pissed me off as well. But think about it again. It feels a bit liberating at the same time, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I started using a tool called Tab Suspender even before I adopted the Tab Zero strategy. It simply suspends any tab that is open for more than x time. You can refresh it and it will load again. It brings a massive improvement in memory consumption. You can find a few more tools, suggestions on solving this problem and an explanation of why exactly &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.trello.com/too-many-browser-tabs&quot;&gt;many open tabs keep your brain ineffective on the Trello blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Matej Latin</name></author><category term="personal-notes" /><category term="Productivity" /><summary type="html">Lots of tabs = chaos</summary></entry></feed>
